<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tractatus, de facultatibus simplicium, the second part of the treatise of the nature and qualitie of such physical simples as are most frequently used in medicines. Methodically handled for the benefit of those that understand not the Latine tongue. To which is added many compound medicines for many diseases incident to manking; as also an alphabetical table at the latter end very necessary for the reader. By Robert Pemell practicioner of physick, at Cranebrooke in Kent.</title>
            <title>Tractatus de simplicium medicamentorum facultatibus. Part 2</title>
            <author>Pemell, Robert.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 153 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90382</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1134</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E721_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207213</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866281</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866281</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118548</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90382)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118548)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 111:E721[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Tractatus, de facultatibus simplicium, the second part of the treatise of the nature and qualitie of such physical simples as are most frequently used in medicines. Methodically handled for the benefit of those that understand not the Latine tongue. To which is added many compound medicines for many diseases incident to manking; as also an alphabetical table at the latter end very necessary for the reader. By Robert Pemell practicioner of physick, at Cranebrooke in Kent.</title>
                  <title>Tractatus de simplicium medicamentorum facultatibus. Part 2</title>
                  <author>Pemell, Robert.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[76] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Legatt, for Philemon Stephens, at the guilded Lion in Pauls Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Second leaf signed: Aaa 2; intended to be bound with part 1.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nouemb. 29".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Formulae, receipts, prescriptions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118548:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TRACTATUS, <hi>De facultatibus Simplicium,</hi> The Second Part Of the TREATISE Of the Nature and Qualitie of ſuch <hi>Phyſical Simples</hi> as are moſt frequently uſed in MEDICINES.</p>
            <p>Methodically handled for the benefit of thoſe that underſtand not the <hi>Latine Tongue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which is added many <hi>Compound Medicines</hi> for many diſeaſes incident to Mankind; as alſo an Alphabe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Table at the latter end very neceſſary for the READER.</p>
            <p>By <hi>ROBERT PEMELL</hi> Practitioner of <hi>Phyſick,</hi> at <hi>Cranebrooke</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Qui poteſt mederi Simplicibus,</l>
               <l>fruſtra quaerit Compoſita.</l>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>J. Legatt,</hi> for <hi>Philemon Stephens,</hi> at the guilded Lion in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:118548:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118548:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Kind Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Had not thought to have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten any thing more of this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, but when I had finiſhed my firſt Part, after examination, I found that I had omitted ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny uſeful and neceſſary <hi>Simples;</hi> I have there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now wrote of the Nature of ſuch onely as I omitted before, for the more readie find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of what is contained in this Second Part. Here followeth a Table of the <hi>Simples,</hi> and the Chapter wherein they are handled. Now my heartie deſire is, that this and the former Treatiſe may be helpful to any that ſhall make uſe of them. Deſiring thy prayers for me, I take my leave of thee.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Febr.</hi> 24. 1652.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Robert Pemell Medicus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:118548:3"/>
            <head>A Table of the <hi>Phyſical Simples</hi> handled in this <hi>Second Part.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>ADders-Tongue,</hi> Chapter 1</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Alliſanders,</hi> chap. 2</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Avens,</hi> chap. 3</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>BRook-Lime,</hi> chap. 4</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bugle,</hi> chap. 5</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CArawayes,</hi> chap. 6</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Celandine the greater and leſſer,</hi> chap. 7</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chervil,</hi> chap. 8</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clarie,</hi> chap. 9</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clove Gilliflowers,</hi> chap. 10</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Colts-foot,</hi> chap. 11</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Coriander-ſeed,</hi> chap. 12</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cowſlips,</hi> chap. 13</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cummin-ſeed,</hi> chap. 14</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>DEvils-bit,</hi> chap. 15</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dropwort,</hi> chap. 16</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Feather-few,</hi> chap. 17</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Golden rod,</hi> chap. 18</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Harts-Tongue,</hi> chap. 19</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>White Houſe-leek,</hi> chap. 20</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hyſop,</hi> chap. 21</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Knotſgraſs,</hi> chap. 22</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>White Lilly,</hi> chap. 23</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lilly Coural,</hi> chap. 24</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Liver wort,</hi> chap. 25</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mouſe eare,</hi> chap. 26</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nep,</hi> chap. 27</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Onions,</hi> chap. 28</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Oſmund Royal,</hi> chap. 29</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>PArſly,</hi> Chapter 30</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pellitorie of the wall,</hi> chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter 31</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Penny royal,</hi> chap. 32</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Periwinkle,</hi> chap. 33</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Poppies garden and wild,</hi> chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, 34</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Quincies,</hi> chap. 35</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>SAge of Ieruſalem,</hi> chapter 36</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sanicle,</hi> or <hi>Sanickle,</hi> chap. 37</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Savine,</hi> chap. 38</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Savorie,</hi> chap. 39</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Saxifrage, Engliſh or common,</hi> chap. 40</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Scabions,</hi> chap. 41</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Scurvie graſſe,</hi> chap. 42</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Shepherds purſe,</hi> chap. 43</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Smallage,</hi> chap. 44</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sorrel,</hi> chap. 45</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Spinage,</hi> chap. 46</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Succorie,</hi> chap. 47</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>TAmarisk,</hi> chap. 48</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tanſie,</hi> chap. 49</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thime,</hi> chap. 50</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VEx vain,</hi> chap. 51</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Violets,</hi> chap. 52</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>WAtercreſſes,</hi> chap. 53</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wood-ſage,</hi> chap. 54</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wood ſorrel,</hi> chap. 55</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:118548:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The ſecond Part,</hi> Of the Nature of Phyſical Simples.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. Of <hi>Adders</hi> tongue.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is called in Latine, <hi>Lingua Serpentis,</hi> or <hi>Serpentina,</hi> in Engliſh <hi>Adders</hi> tongue, or <hi>Serpents</hi> tongue. It is tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate between heat and cold, and drie in the ſecond Degree.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The juice of the Leaves given to drink with the diſtilled Water of Horſe-tail, is a ſingular remedie for all manner of wounds in the breaſt or bowels, or any other part of the body. It is with no leſs good ſucceſs given to thoſe that are much given to caſting or vomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and alſo to thoſe that void blood at the mouth or noſe, or otherwiſe downwards, the ſaid juice or dried leaves made into powder, and given in the diſtilled Water of Oaken buds, is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good for ſuch women as have their uſual Courſes, or the Whites come down too abundantly upon them; the ſaid powder of the Herb taken for ſome time together doth cure Ruptures. A Decoction of the leaves made with water and taken, is good againſt hot Fevers and inward inflammations and heats.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118548:4"/>
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The green Herb infuſed or boyled in red or white wine, and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie eyes waſhed therewith, or dropped therein, taketh away the watering, and cooleth any inflammation that cometh thereby. The leaves mixed with Hogs-greaſe and gently boyled and ſtrained, is good againſt burnings, hot tumours and Apoſtumes, ſpreading ſores, and wild-fire. With the green leaves infuſed in Oyle Olive, and ſet in the Sun for certain dayes, or boyled ſufficiently in the ſame Oyle, is made an excellent green Oyle or Balſame ſingular good for all green and freſh wounds, as alſo for old and inveterate Ulcers, quickly to cure them, eſpecially if a little clear Turpentine be diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved therein.</p>
                  <p>The ſame alſo ſtayeth and repreſſeth all Inflammations that riſe upon pains, by any hurt or wounds.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch things as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>Oyle of <hi>Adders</hi> tongue. The diſtilled Water.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 2. Of <hi>Alliſanders.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine, <hi>Hyppoſelinum,</hi> and <hi>Petroſelinum Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drinum;</hi> in Engliſh, Alexanders, Alexandre, and Alliſanders.</p>
                  <p>The root and ſeeds are hot and dry in the third Degree, they clenſe and make thin.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Alliſanders,</hi> are much uſed to make broth with the upper part of the root and the leaves being boyled together: ſome eat them raw with Vinegar, or ſtew them, and ſo eat them, and this chiefly in the time of Lent to help to digeſt the Crudities and viſcous hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours that are gathered in the Stomach by the much uſe of Fiſh at that time; it doth alſo warm any other cold Stomach, and by the bitterneſs helpeth to open ſtoppings of the Liver, and Spleen, to move Womens courſes, to expel the after Birth, to break wind, to provoke urine and help the ſtrangury, and theſe things the Seed will do likewiſe, if taken in Wine or boyled in Wine, and ſo taken, and is effectual againſt the bitings of Serpents. The roots preſerved in a pickle of Vineger and Salt, are a very wholſome ſauce with
<pb facs="tcp:118548:4"/>
meats, ſtirring up the Appetite, cleanſing and comforting the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach and remove ſtoppings. They are convenient for every age and conſtitution, eſpecially for the Phlegmatick and ſuch as are ſubject to ſtoppings.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Doſe.</head>
                  <p>The Seed is given in powder from a ſcruple to two ſcruples; In Decoction from a dram to two drams.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 3. Of <hi>Avens.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine <hi>Caryophillata,</hi> and that from the Sent of the Root ſo near reſembling Cloves; in Engliſh Avens and herb Bennet. The roots and leaves are manifeſtly drie and ſomething hot, with a clenſing qualitie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>A Decoction of the root or leaves being taken helpeth the diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the breaſt, ſtitches of the ſide, and to expel crude or raw hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours from the Stomach and Belly. It alſo diſſolveth congealed blood, happening by fals or bruiſes, and the ſpitting of blood, and helpeth all inward wounds, comforteth the heart, and ſtrengthneth the ſtomach and a cold brain, and therefore is good in the Spring time to open ſtoppings of the Liver and Spleen, helpeth the wind Collick, Fluxes of the Belly and Ruptures, and is good againſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectious vapours of the Plague and poyſon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>A Decoction of the root made in Wine helpeth wounds and Ulcers though Fiſtulous, if they be waſhed therewith. If foule ſpots or marks in the face, or other parts of the body be waſhed therewith, it taketh them away and leaveth the skin well coloured. The powder of the dried roots, or the juice of them when they are freſh worketh the ſame effects, and in callous Ulcers with the juice of the roots, if a little Verdigreaſe be added, it worketh a good effect.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118548:5"/>
                  <head>The hurtfull qualitie.</head>
                  <p>It is hurtfull for Cholerick perſons, and ſuch as have windie bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and their bowels ſtopt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Doſe.</head>
                  <p>The root is given from a ſcruple to a dram, in powder.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 4. Of <hi>Brook-lime.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine, <hi>Becabunga,</hi> in Engliſh Brook-lime. It is hot and dry like Watercreſſes yet not ſo much.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>Brook-lime and Watercreſſes are generally uſed together, much in Diet <hi>Beeres</hi> and <hi>Ales,</hi> with other things ſerving to purge and clenſe the blood from thoſe ill humours that would overthrow the health thereof; It is very uſeful in the Scurvie, breaks the Stone, provokes Urine and Womens Courſes, and expels the dead Birth. It doth profit much in the Dropſie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>Being fried with Butter and Vinegar, and applied warm, it help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all manner of tumours and ſwellings, and Saint Anthonies fire alſo if it be often renewed. The hearb boyled maketh a good Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation for the ſmollen Legs and the Dropſie. The leaves boyled and ſtamped in a ſtone morter with the powder of Fenegreek, Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeed, the roots of Mariſh, Mallowes, and ſome Hogs greaſe, unto the form of a Pultis, taketh away any ſwelling in leg or arm; wounds alſo that are ready to fall into Apoſtemation it mightily defendeth that no humour or accident ſhall happen thereunto. Farriers doe uſe it about their horſes to take away ſwellings, to heal the ſcab, and other like diſeaſes in them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch things as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The juice. The ſyrupe which is thus made; Take of the juice of Brook-lime, and of the juice of Scurvie-graſſe, of each a pound and a half, of Sugar one pound or one pound and an half; clarifie the juice with the white of an Egg, and then boyl it to a ſyrupe; of
<pb facs="tcp:118548:5"/>
which take a ſpoonfull morning and Evening. This is excellent in the Scurvie.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 5. Of <hi>Bugle.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine, <hi>Bugula Conſolida, media;</hi> in Engliſh, Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, or brown Bugle, and middle Cumfrey or Conſound. It is temperate in heat, but drying moderately, and ſomewhat aſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>It is of excellent uſe for ſuch as have caught any fall, or are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly bruiſed, for it diſſolveth the congealed blood, and diſperſeth it by taking the Decoction of the leaves and flowers made in wine; the ſame is no leſſe effectual for any inward wounds, thruſts or ſtabs into the body or bowels, and is an eſpecial help in all wound drinks, as alſo for thoſe that are Liver-grown as they call it, which ariſeth from the ſtoppings of the Liver and Gall, and ſtrengthning the parts afterwards. It helpeth the Jaundiſe and Ruptures, as alſo ſuch as have broken any bone.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>It is wonderful in curing all manner of Ulcers and Sores, whether new or freſh or old, yea Gangreens and Fiſtulaes alſo, either the leaves bruiſed and applied, or their juice uſed to waſh and bathe the places; and the ſame made into a lotion with ſome Hony of Roſes and Allom cureth all ſores of the mouth and gums, be they never ſo foul or of long continuance: it worketh no leſſe effectually for Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Sores in the ſecret parts of Men and Women. It helpeth broken bones, being thereto applied. An Ointment made with the leaves of Bugle, Scabious, and Sanicle, bruiſed and boyled in Hogs greaſe until the herbs be drie, and then ſtrained forth and kept in a pot, is found ſo ſingular good for all ſorts of hurts in the body, that I would not wiſh any (that deſire to doe good to themſelves or others) to be without it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:118548:6"/>
               <head>CHAP. 6. Of <hi>Carawayes.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine, <hi>Carum, Careum,</hi> but uſually <hi>Carvum;</hi> in Engliſh Caraway, Carawayes, and Caruway. Caraway ſeeds are hot and drie as <hi>Galen</hi> ſaith, almoſt in the third Degree, and have withall a moderate ſharp qualitie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Duration.</head>
                  <p>The Seeds will keep good a year or two.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>Caraway-ſeed breaketh wind, provoketh urine, and is pleaſant and comfortable to the ſtomach, helping digeſtion, and alſo condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth to all cold griefs of the head and ſtomach the bowels or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as alſo the wind in them, and helpeth to ſharpen the eye ſight. It is good in the ſwimming of the head. The ſeeds are much uſed in Bread, Cakes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to give a reliſh to them. Caraway Comfits are of the ſame nature.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The powder of the ſeed put into a Poultis, taketh away black and blew ſpots of blowes or bruiſes. The herb it ſelf or with ſome of the ſeed bruiſed and fryed, laid hot in a double cloth to the lower parts of the belly doth eaſe the pain of the wind Collick.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The hurtful qualitie.</head>
                  <p>They muſt not be uſed in very hot and drie bodies.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch things, as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled water of the herb. Caraway, Comfits, Chymicall Oyle.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 7. Of <hi>Celandine,</hi> the greater and leſſer.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>THe greater is called <hi>Chelidonium majus,</hi> and <hi>Hirundinaria ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor;</hi> in Engliſh, great Celandine. It is hot and drie in the third Degree, and of a cleanſing facultie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:118548:6"/>The leſſer is called in Latine <hi>Chelidonium minus,</hi> and <hi>Hirundina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria minor;</hi> in Engliſh, ſmall Celandine and Pilewort. It is not ſo hot as the greater.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The greater Celandine openeth the ſtoppings of the Liver and Gall, and thereby helpeth the yellow Jaundies, the herb or the roots being boyled in white wine with a few Anniſeeds and drunk; the ſame helpeth the Dropſie, Itch and ſores in the legs, or other parts of the body. The juice taken faſting with Sugar or the diſtilled wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, is commended againſt the Plague or Peſtilence, eſpecially if a little good Treacle be mixed therewith, and they upon the taking thereof laid down to ſweat a little.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The juice dropped in the eyes doth clenſe them from films and clouds that darken them, but it is beſt to mixe with it a little breaſt milk: It is good in old filthy eating ulcers in any place to ſtay their fretting and running, and to cauſe them to heal the more ſpeedily: the juice often applied to Tetters, Ringworms, or ſuch like, will quickly kill their ſharpneſſe, and heal them alſo; and it taketh away Warts alſo being rubbed on them. The herb with the roots bruiſed and heated with Oyle of Camomil, and applied to the Navil, taketh away the griping pain in the belly, and all pains of the mother, and applied to Womens breaſts that have their Courſes too much, ſtayeth them; the juice or the Decoction of the herb gargled between the teeth that ake taketh away the pain, and the powder of the dried root laid upon an aking hollow or looſe tooth, will as they ſay cauſe it quickly to fall out: the juice mixed with ſome powder of Brimſtone cureth the itch, and taketh away all the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lourings of the skin whatſoever, be they ſpots or marks of bruiſes, ſtripes or wounds, the Morphew alſo, Sun-burning or any the like.</p>
                  <p>Pilewort doth wonderfully help the Piles or Hemorrhoides, as alſo kernels by the ears and throat, called the Kings-evil, or any other hard wens or tumours, either the Decoction of the leaves and roots, or an ointment made of them with Hogs greaſe, or freſh Butter and uſed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Poultis against Cancrous ſores of Womens breaſts.</head>
                  <p>Take of the juice of Celandine, and Gooſ-dung, of each a like quantitie, mix them together and apply it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118548:7"/>
                  <head>An Injection, good in the cure of hollow wounds.</head>
                  <p>Take of Celandine, Sage, Saint Johns Wort, of each half a hand, ful, Elecampane root four ounces, Vineger a pint, Water ſix pints boyl them till near half be conſumed, add thereto of Honie a pound, Aloes in fine powder foure ounces; let them boyle gently a while, then keep it for your uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch things as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled water; Juice, Salt.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 8. Of <hi>Chervill.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine, <hi>Cerefolium, Cerifolium</hi> and <hi>Chaerifolium;</hi> in Engliſh Chervil, and Chervel. It is of a temperate heat and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate drineſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>It doth moderately warm the ſtomach, and it is a certain remedy ſaith <hi>Tragus</hi> to diſſolve congealed or clotted blood in the body after fals or bruiſes, if the juice or the diſtilled water thereof be drunk: it is taken alſo by divers to be good to provoke urine, and to expel the ſtone in the kidneyes and Womens Courſes, taken either in meat or drink and moreover to help the Pleuriſie and prickings of the. The round tufts or heads which contain the ſeeds, do far excel the leaves, and may be eaten as a ſallad by themſelves with Oyle Olive, Vineger and Pepper, for they are very good for a cold and weak ſtomach. The roots boyled and eaten as before with Oyle, Vinegar and pepper are good for a weak ſtomach, for weak and aged perſons, and for ſuch as are dull and without courage; for they delight the ſtomach, comfort the heart, increaſe ſtrength, and ſtir up <hi>Venus</hi> or Luſt. A Decoction of Chervil taken, provoketh ſleep ſweetly.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>Being bruiſed and applied, it diſſolveth any tumours or ſwellings in any part of the body, as alſo to take away the ſpots and marks in the fleſh and skin of congealed blood by bruiſes or blowes in a ſhort ſpace, and alſo eaſeth the Collick and pain of the belly.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118548:7"/>
                  <head>Of ſuch Medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled Water; Salt of Chervil.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 9. Of <hi>Clarie.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine, <hi>Horminum</hi> and <hi>Orminum;</hi> in Engliſh, Clary, or Cleere eye. It is hot and drie in the third Degree.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The Seeds or the Leaves boyled in Wine and taken provoketh to Venery. It is much in uſe with Men or Women that have weak backs to help to ſtrengthen the Reins, either uſed by it ſelf, or with other Herbs that conduce to the ſame effect, and in Tanſies often, or the freſh Leaves fried in Butter, being firſt dipped in a batter of Flower, Eggs, and a little Milke, ſerved as a diſh to the Table, is not unpleaſant to any, but exceeding profitable for weak backs. It provoketh Womens Courſes, and bringeth away the after Birth. It is uſed in <hi>Italy</hi> to help Barrenneſſe, when it proceeds from a cold and moiſt Diſpoſition; it ſtayeth the Whites, and helpeth alſo a cold ſtomach oppreſſed with cold Flegme, purgeth the Head of Rheume and much corruption.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The manner of Adminiſtring it.</head>
                  <p>It is chiefly uſed in Decoction.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The Seeds made in fine Powder put into the eye Eye alone, or mixed with Honey and ſo uſed cleareth the Sight, and taketh away white or red ſpots therein. The Muſcilage of the Seed made with VVater and applied to tumours or ſwellings, diſperſeth and taketh them away, and alſo draweth forth ſplinters, thorns or other things gotten into the fleſh; the Leaves uſed with Vinegar either by it ſelf, or with a little Hony, doth help hot inflammations, if timely
<pb facs="tcp:118548:8"/>
applied. The powder of the dried Leaves put into the Noſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voketh ſneeſing, and thereby purgeth the Head and Brain of much Rheume and Corruption.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The hurtful qualitie.</head>
                  <p>The frequent uſe of Clary offendeth the head, and is hurtful for the brain and memorie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Clownes Wound-wort</hi> or <hi>All-heale,</hi> See my Help for the Poor, page 10.11, 12, 13, 14.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 10. Of <hi>Clove gillowflowers.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>THey are called in Latin, <hi>Caryophilli;</hi> in Engliſh Clovegillow-flowers, They are temperate in heat and drineſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Duration.</head>
                  <p>They will keep good a year being well dried.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>They are very Cordial, and much in uſe in Feavers both peſtilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial and others, in faintneſſe of the heart and ſpirits.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The ſyrupe is of the ſame Nature.</head>
                  <p>The Flowers being pickled with Vinegar and Sugar are a pleaſant and dainty ſauce, ſtir up the Appetite, and are alſo of a Cordial fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>They are uſed in wounds of the Head, they draw out pieces of bones the Skul being broken, eaſe the Head-ache and pain of the Teeth, being thereto applied.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Medicines made thereof.</head>
                  <p>Syrupe, Conſerve, Vinegar.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:118548:8"/>
               <head>CHAP. 11. Of <hi>Colts-foot.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperaments.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine, <hi>Tuſſilago,</hi> and <hi>Tarfara;</hi> in Engliſh, Colts-foot, Horſ-foot and Fole-foot. Being freſh it is cooling and drying, but when it is drie, it is ſomewhat hot and drie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Duration.</head>
                  <p>The Leaves and Flowers being dry will keep good a year.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The drie Leaves are beſt for ſuch as have thinne Rheumes and Diſtillations upon the Lungs cauſing the Cough thereby to thicken and drie it. The freſh Leaves, or Juice, or Syrupe made thereof, is fitteſt for an hot dry Cough, and for wheeſing and ſhortneſſe of breath; the dried Leaves taken as Tobacco is in the like manner good for the thinne Rheumes, Diſtillations and Coughs, as alſo the Root taken in like ſort. The diſtilled Water hereof ſimply or with Elder Flowers and Nightſhade is a ſingular remedie againſt all hot Agues, to drink two ounces at a time.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled Water ſimply or with Elder Flowers and Night<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhade helpeth the pains of the head proceeding from heat, if Clothes be wet therein and applied thereto. The ſame alſo appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to any hot ſwelling or inflammation doth much good, yea it helpeth Saint Anthonies fire, and burning alſo, and is ſingular good to take away wheales and ſmall puſhes, that riſe through heat, as alſo againſt the burning heat of the Piles, or of the privie parts, to apply wet clothes therein to the places. The fume of the dried Leaves or Roots taken through a Tunnel, burned upon coals effectually, helpeth thoſe that are troubled with ſhortneſſe of breath and fetch their wind thick and often, and breaketh the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtumes of the breaſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch Medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled Water, Syrupe both Simple and Compound, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve made of the Flowers.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:118548:9"/>
               <head>CHAP. 12. Of <hi>Coriander-ſeed.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine, <hi>Semen Coriandri;</hi> in Engliſh, Coriander, and Coliander-ſeed. It is hot and dry in the firſt or ſecond Degree.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Duration</head>
                  <p>They will keep good two or three years.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>Theſe Seeds being taken in VVine killeth VVorms, increaſeth Blood and Sperme: It is alſo good againſt the Serpent called <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phisbaena.</hi> It is comfortable to the Stomach, by heating and drying the cold and moiſture thereof, helpeth the Digeſtion, and expreſſeth the Vapours therein that riſe upwards, and reſiſteth forcible pains of the VVind Collick and the ſtopping of Urine: They are very convenient for cold Phlegmatick and Rheumatick bodies.</p>
                  <p>Coriander Comfits taken after meat cloſeth up the mouth of the ſtomach, ſtayeth vomiting, and helpeth digeſtion.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Seeds muſt be prepared before they are uſed, which is done by ſteeping them all night and a day in wine Vinegar, and then dry them and keep them for your uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The hurtfull Qualitie.</head>
                  <p>They are counted hurtful for ſuch as have the Head-ache, Falling-ſickneſſe, and ſwimming of the Head.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch things as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>Coriander Comfits, Chymical Oyle.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:118548:9"/>
               <head>CHAP. 13. Of <hi>Cowſlips.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called, in Latine, <hi>Herba Paralyſis;</hi> in Engliſh, Cowſlip. They are moderately drie, and a little hot.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Duration.</head>
                  <p>They will keep good a year.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>They are uſed in the Apoplexie, Palſie, and ſuch like diſeaſes of the head, in arthritical Pains, Gouts and Convulſions. The roots made into a Decoction and taken, eaſeth the pains of the back and bladder, opening the paſſages of Urine which was the cauſe thereof. The juice of the leaves is good for ſuch as have their inward parts hurt, rent or broken. The conſerve of Cowſlip is profitable in the Palſey, Apoplexie, weakneſſe of the Joynts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The juice of the Flowers, or the diſtilled water is uſed to cleanſe the skin from ſpots or diſcolourings therein, as alſo to take away the wrinckles thereof, and cauſe the skin to become ſmooth and fair. The Flowers or Leaves bruiſed and applied helpeth the joynt-gout, and ſwellings that ariſe from the ſtinging of venemous crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. An Ointment or Oyle made with the juice of Cowſlips and Linſeed Oyle, cureth burnings and ſcaldings.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch things as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>Conſerve of Cowſlip, The diſtilled Water, Syrupe, Oyle by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, Vineger.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 14. Of <hi>Cummin-ſeed.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine <hi>Caminum,</hi> and <hi>Cyminum;</hi> in Engliſh, Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min-ſeed. It is hot and drie in the third Degree.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118548:10"/>
                  <head>The Duration.</head>
                  <p>It will keep good two or three years.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>Cummin-ſeed diſſolveth wind in the body, and eaſeth the pains of the Collick, being boyled in Wine and drunk, and is uſed as a correctour of any windie meats: it helpeth alſo thoſe that are bitten by Serpents taken in the ſame manner. The ſame taken in Beere or Poſſet drink, is good for thoſe that are ſhort winded, or are otherwiſe troubled with an old cough, or the diſeaſe of the breaſt, to boyle the ſame with Figs in Wine. It is very uſeful in the Dropſie called Tympanie, and in giddineſſe of the head.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>Being boyled in Wine, and ſo made into a Poultis, it taketh the ſwellings of the Codds by wind or a wateriſh humour, if it be applied thereto with Barley meale. It helpeth alſo other cold pains and ſwellings being thus applied. It ſtoppeth bleeding of the noſe being mixed with Vinegar and ſmelt to and boyled in Water and the lower parts bathed therewith, ſtayeth the bounding Courſes of Women. Cummin-ſeed bruiſed and fried with an hard Egg, and laid to the nod of the neck, eaſeth an old head-ache, and ſtayeth the rheume that falleth into the eyes, or are blood-ſhotten, or elſe the powder mixed with wax into the form of a Plaſter, and appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed warm to the eyes will ſoon help it and take it away. Being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to the belly with Wine and Barley meale boyled together to the form of a Poultis, it eaſeth the gripings and torments of the belly. Being quilted in a little bag with a ſmal quantitie of Bay ſalt, and made hot upon a Bed-pan with fire or ſuch like, and ſprinkled with good Wine Vinegar, and applied to the ſide very hot, it taketh away the ſtitch and pains thereof, and eaſeth the Pleuriſie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The hurtfull qualitie.</head>
                  <p>It muſt not be uſed in very hot dry and chollerick bodies. If it be much uſed either inwardly or outwardly, it is ſaid to make the party look pale.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The <hi>Species Diacuminu.</hi> Chymical Oyle.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:118548:10"/>
               <head>CHAP. 15. Of <hi>Devils-bit.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperaments.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine <hi>Morſus Diaboli,</hi> and <hi>Succiſa;</hi> in Engliſh, Devils-bit, and Forebit. It is hot and dry in the ſecond Degree:</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Duration.</head>
                  <p>It will keep good a yeare.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>It is very profitable againſt the Plague and all Peſtilential diſeaſes, or poyſons, and the bitings of venemous beaſts, the hearb or root being boyled in Wine and drunk: the ſame alſo helps thoſe that are inwardly bruiſed by any fal, or cruſht by any caſualtie diſſolving the clotted or congeald blood, and voyding it by ſtool or otherwiſe. The Decoction of the Hearb wherein ſome Hony of Roſes is put, is very effectual to help inveterate tumours and ſwellings of the Almonds and throat, which do hardly come to ripeneſſe, for it digeſteth, cleanſeth and conſumeth the flegme ſticking thereto: It helpeth alſo to procure womens Courſes, and to eaſe all pains of the Mother, to break winds therein, and in the bowels. The powder of the root taken in Beere or Poſſet drink driveth forth VVorms in the body. It is uſeful in the Falling-ſickneſſe, French Poxe, and inward wounds The diſtilled water is effectual for the aforeſaid diſeaſes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The manner of adminiſtering it.</head>
                  <p>It is chiefly given in Decoction.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The Hearb or Root bruiſed and applyed taketh away the black and blew marks after bruiſes and ſuch like. A decoction of the Hearb with ſome Hony of Roſes mixed therein, helpeth tumour and ſwellings of the throat and Almonds, if the mouth and throat be often gargled or waſhed therewith. The juice or diſtilled water of the Hearb, is as effectual for green wounds and old ſores, as the Scabiouſes be, and cleanſeth the head from ſcurffe and ſores, and the skin from itches, pimples, freckles, Morphew, or other deformities thereof, but eſpecially if a little Vitriol be diſſolved therein.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118548:11"/>
                  <head>The Doſe.</head>
                  <p>It is given in Powder from half a dram to a dram.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch Medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled Water; The Juice.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 16. Of <hi>Dropwort.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine, <hi>Filipendula</hi> and <hi>Philipendula;</hi> in Engliſh, Philipendula and Dropwort. It is hot and drie in the third De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, opening and cleanſing, yet a little binding: It is called Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort, becauſe it helpeth ſuch as have their Urine ſtopt and piſſe by drops.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Duration.</head>
                  <p>It will keep good a yeare.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>It is very effectual to provoke Urine, as alſo to help the Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurie and all other pains of the Bladder and Reins, helping mightily to break and expel the Stone, either in the Kidneyes or Bladder, and alſo to bring away the gravel, whether you uſe the Flowers, Leaves or Seed, but the Roots are moſt effectual, either taken in Powder, or in a Decoction with white Wine, whereunto a little Honey is added. The ſame helpeth to expel the after-Birth, is good in the Jaundiſe and Falling-ſickneſſe, The Roots made into Powder and mixed with Honey into the form of an Electuarie, doth much help them whoſe ſtomacks are ſwollen, breaking and diſſolving the wind which was the cauſe thereof, as alſo is very effectual for all the diſeaſes of the Lungs, as ſhortneſſe of Breath, wheeſings, hoarſeneſſe of the throat, and the Cough, and to bring away cold Flegme there-from, or any other parts there-abouts.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The manner of Adminiſtring it.</head>
                  <p>It is given in Powder, or Decoction chiefly.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118548:11"/>
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>Being bruiſed and applied it helpeth the ſwelling of the Piles or Hemorrhoides.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Doſe.</head>
                  <p>It is given in powder from half a dram to a dram.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch Medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled Water.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 17. Of <hi>Featherfew.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine <hi>Parthemium, matricatia,</hi> and <hi>Febrifuga;</hi> becauſe it expels Feavers or Agues; in Engliſh, Featherfew and Feaverfew. It is hot and dry in the third Degree, or hot in the third Degree and dry in the ſecond: it cleanſeth, purgeth, or ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth, openeth and fully performeth all that bitter things can do.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>It is chiefly uſed for the diſeaſes of the mother, whether it be the riſing of the Mother, or the hardneſſe or inflammations of the ſame, if a Decoction of the flowers or herbs be made in wine with a little Nutmeg or Mace put therein, and drunk often in a day: the ſame bringeth down the Courſes alſo ſpeedily, and warmeth thoſe parts oppreſſed by ſtoppings or cold, as alſo helpeth to expel the dead Birth and the after Birth. A Decoction thereof taken with Sugar or Hony helpeth the cough and ſtuffing of the cheſt by cold, as alſo to cleanſe the reins in them. The powder of the herb (ſaith <hi>Dioſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rides</hi>) taken in wine with ſome Oxymel, or Water and Honie, purgeth like to Epithymum both Choller and Flegme, and is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailable for thoſe that are ſhort winded and are troubled with melancholly and heavineſſe, or ſadneſſe of the ſpirits. It is very effectual for the ſwimming of the head and winde in the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, and is frequently given before the fits of Agues. It is good in the Dropſey, and helpeth ſuch as are impotent in
<pb facs="tcp:118548:12"/>
venereous acts, It is a good remedie againſt <hi>Opium</hi> taken too liberally,</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The manner of Adminiſtring.</head>
                  <p>It is chiefly given in Decoction.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>Being applied outwardly to the Mother, it helpeth the riſing thereof, the hardneſſe or inflammation of the ſame, and bringeth down Womens Courſes, the Birth and after Birth, if a Woman ſit over the hot Fumes of the Decoction of the herb made in water or wine. It is effectual for all cold pains of the head, the herb be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bruiſed and applyed to che crown of the head. It is a frequent cuſtome to apply the herb bruiſed with Glaſſe and Bay-ſalt to the wriſts of the hands, before the fits of Agues. The ſame bruiſed and heated on a tile with a little wine to moyſten it, or fried with a little Oyle and wine in a frying-pan, and applied warm to the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach or belly expelleth wind and griping pains. The diſtilled wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is uſed to take away ſpots, freckles and other deformities of the skin.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The hurtfull qualitie.</head>
                  <p>It muſt not be uſed in very hot and drie bodies.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch Medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled Water.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Filipendula,</hi> See Dropwort.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 18. Of <hi>Golden Rod.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine, <hi>Virga aurea;</hi> in Engliſh, Golden Rod. It is hot and dry almoſt in the ſecond Degree.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Duration.</head>
                  <p>It will keep good a year.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>It is much in uſe againſt the ſtone in the Kidneyes, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke Urine, as alſo to bring away gravel. The Decoction of the
<pb facs="tcp:118548:12"/>
herb green or drie, or the diſtilled water thereof is very effectual for inward bruiſes, and ſtayeth bleedings in any part of the body, and of wounds alſo, and Fluxes in women, and fluxes of the belly, as alſo the bloody flix in man or woman, availeth in Ruptures, and is a ſoveraign wound herb.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The manner of Adminiſtering it.</head>
                  <p>It is given chiefly in Decoction.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The green herb bruiſed and applied helpeth bruiſes, bleeding at the noſe or wounds bleeding, Fluxes of the belly and Ruptures. It healeth green wounds quickly, or old ſores and ulcers that are hard to be cured, which often come by flux of moiſt humours thereunto, and hinder them from healing: it is likewiſe uſeful in all lotions for ſores or ulcers in the mouth or throat, or in the privie parts of Man or Woman: the Decoction thereof likewiſe helpeth to faſten the teeth that are looſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch things as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled water.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 19. Of <hi>Harts-tongue.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperaments.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine, <hi>Lingua Cervina,</hi> and <hi>Phyllitis,</hi> in Engliſh, Harts-tongue. It is cold and drying.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>It is commended againſt the hardneſſe and ſtopping of the Liver and Spleen, and againſt the heat of the Liver and Stomach, it is very good alſo againſt lasks and the bloody flux, and ſpitting of blood. <hi>Dioſcorides</hi> ſaith, it is good againſt the biting of Serpents: The leaves are green almoſt all the yeare. The diſtilled water is commended againſt the paſſions of the heart, and to ſtay the Hicket.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The manner of Adminiſtring it.</head>
                  <p>It is chiefly uſed in Decoction.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118548:13"/>
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled water thereof is ſaid to help the falling of the Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, and to ſtay the bleeding of the gums, if the mouth be gargled therewith. The herb or the juice applied doth mundifie or cleanſe wounds and ulcers.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch Medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled water of the leaves.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 20. Of <hi>White Houſe-leek.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine <hi>Sempervivum,</hi> and <hi>ſedum majus,</hi> in Engliſh, Houſeleek and ſengreen. It is cold in the third Degree, moderate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly drying and binding.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The juice thereof taken with Sugar, or a Poſſet made with the juice is ſingular good in all hot Agues and inflammations, for it cooles and temperateth the blood and ſpirits, quenches thirſt, helpeth fluxes of the belly, ſtayeth the Courſes in women, killeth worms, and is good againſt the biting of the <hi>Phalangium</hi> Spider. The di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilled water is profitable for the purpoſes aforeſaid.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The juice dropped into the eyes, is good to ſtay all hot defluxions of ſharp and ſalt rheume into them. It cooleth inflammations, Saint <hi>Anthonies</hi> fire, and all other hot corruption in the fleſh, ſcaldings alſo and burnings, the ſhingles, fretting Ulcers, Cankers, Tetters, Ringworms and the like, eaſeth the hot gout. The juice taketh away warts and Corns being often bathed rherewith, and the skin of the leavs being laid on afterwards: it eaſeth the headache, and diſtempered heat of the brain in Frenſies, or for want of reſt, being applied to the temples or forehead: the leaves bruiſed and laid upon the crown or ſeam of the head ſtayeth bleeding at the noſe very quickly. The leavs being gently rubd on any ſtung with netles or bees,
<pb facs="tcp:118548:13"/>
or any venemous Creature, doth preſently take away the pain. The diſtilled water of the herb is good for the purpoſes aforeſaid.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch Medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled water. The Juice, Syrupe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 21. Of <hi>Hyſope.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperaments.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine, <hi>Hyſſopus</hi> and <hi>Hyſſopum;</hi> in Engliſh, Hyſope, and Hyſſope. It is hot and drie in the third Degree.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Duration.</head>
                  <p>It will keep good a year being dried.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>Hyſope boyled with Rue and Hony, and drunk, doth help thoſe that are troubled with Coughs, ſhortneſſe of breath, wheeſing and Rheumatick diſtillations upon the Lungs; taken alſo with Ory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel, or water and honey, it purgeth groſſe humours by the ſtool, and with honey killeth worms in the belly. It amendeth the native colour of the body ſpoyled by the yellow Jaundiſe, helpeth the Dropſie and the Spleen, if it be taken with Figs and Nitar. It is good in the Falling-ſickneſſe, provokes Vrine, expels wind, and brings down Womens Courſes, and eaſeth the ſharp fits of Agues. The diſtilled water is good for the ſame diſeaſes, but doth not work ſo effectually as the Decoction. The ſyrupe alſo hath the ſame vertue.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The manner of adminiſtering it.</head>
                  <p>It is given in Pils, Decoction, and in Electuaries.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Pils againſt the Falling-ſickneſſe.</head>
                  <p>Take of Hyſope, Horehound and Caſtoreum of each half a dram, of the Root of <hi>Male Peony</hi> two drams, of <hi>Aſſa-fetida</hi> one ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, with the juice of Hyſope make Pils, and take two or three of them every night ſo long as they laſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118548:14"/>
                  <head>A Decoction, good againſt the Cough and tough Flegme.</head>
                  <p>Take of Hyſope one handful, Figs two Ounces, Sugar-candie one Ounce, boyl them in a quart of Muſcadine, until half a pint be conſumed, ſtrain it, and drink a ſmall draught thereof morning and evening.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>It taketh away black and blew ſpots and marks that come by ſtrokes, bruiſes or fals, being boyled and the places bathed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. It is an excellent Medicine for the Quinſie, to waſh and gargle the throat, being boyled with Figs; it helpeth the Tooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ache, being boyled in Vinegar, and gargled therewith; the hot vapours of the Decoction taken by a Funnel in at the Eares, eaſeth the inflammations of them; <hi>Meſue</hi> ſaith, the ſinging noyſe of them; being bruiſed, and Salt, Honey, and Cummin-ſeed put to it, helpeth thoſe that are ſtung by Serpents. The green Herbs brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed any a little Sugar put to it, doth quickly heal any green wound or cut in the hand, or elſe where. The Oyl thereof being anointed, killeth Lice, and taketh away the itching of the head.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The hurtfull Qualitie.</head>
                  <p>Hot and drie bodies muſt be ſparing in the uſe of it. <hi>Plinie</hi> ſaith, it is an enemy to the ſtomach, and provoketh caſting: it is beſt in the Spring and Winter, and that for aged and Flegmatick perſons, and all ſuch as abound with cold and rheumatick humours.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch Medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled Water, Conſerve of the Flowers. Species <hi>Diahyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopu,</hi> Syrupe both Simple and Compound, Oyle.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 22. Of <hi>Knotgraſſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine, <hi>Polygonum</hi> and <hi>Ceutumnodia,</hi> from the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny joynts or knots that every branch hath. It is cold in the ſecond or third Degree, of a binding Nature.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118548:14"/>
                  <head>The Duration.</head>
                  <p>It will keep good a year.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The Juice or Decoction thereof is moſt effectual to ſtay any bleeding at the mouth, and to cool and temper the heat of the blood, or of the ſtomach, and to ſtay any flux of the blood or hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, either of the belly or womb, as Courſes in Women, or the running of the Reins alſo. The juice given before the Tertian or Quartane Ague comes, is ſaid to drive it away: it is alſo good to provoke Urine when it is ſtopped, as alſo when it paſſeth away by drops, and with pain, and when it is hot and ſharp alſo, to take a dram of the Powder of the Herb in wine for many dayes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: being boyled in Wine and drunk, it helpeth thoſe that are ſtung or bitten by venemous Creatures, and the ſame is very effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual to ſtay all falling down of humours rheumatick upon the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, and killeth Worms in the belly or ſtomach, and eaſeth all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward pains that ariſe from heat, ſharpneſſe and corruption of blood and choller, and is good for inward wounds. The diſtilled water taken by it ſelf, or with the powder of the herb or ſeed is very effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual to all the purpoſes aforeſaid.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The manner of Administring it.</head>
                  <p>It is chiefly given in Decoction.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The juice hereof ſtayeth the bleeding of the noſe being applied to the forehead and temples, or to be ſquirted up into the noſe: the ſame cooleth all manner of inflammations, even Saint <hi>Anthonies</hi> fire, or any other breaking forth of heat, all hot ſwellings and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtumations, all eating and ſweating, or burning ſores and fiſtulous Cancers, or foul filthie Vlcers being applied or put into them, but eſpecially for all ſorts of Vlcers and ſores in the privie parts of Men or Women, reſtraining the humours from falling to them, and cool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and drying up the hot and moiſt inflammations that are apt to to follow ſuch ſores in ſuch places. It keepeth all freſh and green wounds by reſtraining the blood, and quickly cloſeth up the lips of them: the juice dropped into the ears helpeth them wonderfully, although they are foul, and have running matter in them. It helpeth alſo the inflammation of the eyes being put therein.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118548:15"/>
                  <head>The Doſe.</head>
                  <p>The Doſe in Powder is from half a dram to a dram.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled water.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 23. Of <hi>White Lilly.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>It is called in Latine <hi>Lilium Album,</hi> and <hi>Roſa Junonis;</hi> in Engliſh White Lilly. The Leaves or Flowers are hot and moiſt, and partly of a ſubtile ſubſtance, the root is drie in the firſt Degree, and hot in the ſecond.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The Roots boyled in honied water and drunk, driveth forth by the ſiege all corruption of blood, as <hi>Plinie</hi> ſaith, The ſeeds are good to be taken againſt the biting of Serpents, and expelleth the poyſon of the Peſtilence, cauſing it to break forth in bliſters in the outward part of the skin, being taken in VVine, or the roots ſtamped and ſtrained with wine, and given to drinke for two or three dayes together. The juice tempered with Barley meale, and baked in cakes, and ſo eaten ordinarily for a moneth or ſixe weeks together with meat and no other bread during that time is ſaid to cure the Dropſie. The diſtilled water being taken is ſaid to cauſe eaſie and ſpeedy deliverance, and to expel the after Birth. The ſame water is uſed in diſeaſes of the Lungs, ſhortneſſe of Breath, the Cough, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The Root roſted and well mixed with Oyle of Roſes doth ſoften the hardneſſe of the Matrix, and provoketh the Courſes in Women, being laid thereupon. The ſame ſtamped with hony gleweth toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſinewes that be cut in ſunder, conſumeth or ſcoureth away the Vlcers of the head called Achores, and likewiſe all ſcurvineſſe of the beard and face, and is good to be laid to all diſlocations, or places out of joynt. The ſame ſtamped with Vinegar, the leaves of Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bane,
<pb facs="tcp:118548:15"/>
or the meale of Barley, cureth the Tumours and Apoſtumes of the privie members: it bringeth the hair again upon places that have been burned or ſcalded, if it be mingled with oyle or greaſe, and the place anointed therewith: the ſame roſted in Embers, and ſtamped with leaven of Rie bread and Hogs-greaſe, breaketh peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lential botches, and ripeneth Apoſtumes in the flanks, coming of Venery and ſuch like: the ſame mixed with oyle of Roſes cureth wilde-fire, burnings and cloſeth up wounds and ulcers, and is good alſo to be laid upon the biting of Serpents. The ſame boyled in Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar and applied cureth corns.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>To breake a Felon.</head>
                  <p>Take of Sorrel, Marſh Marigold, of each half a handful, white Lilie root a dram bruiſe them and roaſt them in Embers in a Dock leaf; bind it on hot to the places affected. The oyle made of the Flowers, is good to ſupple, mollifie and digeſt, excellent to ſoften the ſinewes, and to cure the hardneſſe of the Matrix. The diſtilled water mixed with Camphor and oyle of Tarter is uſed to beautifie the face.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch Medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled water, Conſerve, Oyle, both ſimple and compound</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 24. Of <hi>Lilly Coural.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called <hi>Lilium Courallium,</hi> in Engliſh, Lilly Coural, Lilly of the Valley, May Lilly, and Liricon fancie. They are hot and dry of complexion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The Flowers diſtilled in wine and drunk the quantitie of a ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful reſtoreth ſpeech to thoſe that have the dumb Palſie, or Apoplexy, and is good againſt the gout and comforteth the heart; it is very profitable in the ſwimming of the head, Palſie and all cold diſeaſes of the head,</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled water thereof helpeth the inflammation of the eyes, being dropped therein. The powder thereof being blown up into
<pb facs="tcp:118548:16"/>
the noſe, is a good Errhine, and doth draw away cold humors from the brain, The flowers put into a glaſſe, and ſet in a hill of Ants cloſe ſtopped for the ſpace of a moneth and then taken out, therein you ſhall find a liquor that eaſeth the pain of the Gout, and helpeth the <hi>Serpigo,</hi> or Titter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch Medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled water, both ſimple and compound Spirit, Conſerve, Oyle Chymical, and by infuſion.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 25. Of <hi>Liverwort.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine <hi>Lichen, Hepatica,</hi> and <hi>Jecoraria,</hi> and that either becauſe it healeth the Lichen Tetters, which deform the skin and make it rough, or from helping the diſeaſes of the Liver. It is cold and dry, and ſomewhat binding.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>It is ſingular good for all the diſeaſes of the Liver, both to cool and cleanſe it, and helpeth alſo inflammations in any part, and the yellow Jaundiſe likewiſe. Liverwort being bruiſed and boyled in ſmall Beere and drunk cooleth the heat of the Liver and Kidneyes, and helps the running of the reins in Men, and the whites in Women. It is good in the hectick Feaver, and all other hot Feavers, as alſo in the Scab, Tetter, and all other running ſores. If it be boyled in Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet drink and taken, it helpeth bleeding at the Noſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The manner of Adminiſtring it:</head>
                  <p>It is chiefly uſed in Decoction.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>It ſtoppeth the bleeding of wounds being applied, and is alſo a ſingular remedy to ſtay the ſpreading of Tetters or Ringworms, and other fretting ſores and ſcabs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch Medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled water.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:118548:16"/>
               <head>CHAP. 26. Of <hi>Mouſeare.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine <hi>Piloſella</hi> and <hi>Auricula muris;</hi> in Engliſh Mouſeare. It is hot and dry, and of a cleanſing, binding and conſolidating quality.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The Juice hereof taken in Wine, or the Decoction thereof drunk doth help the Jaundies, although of long continuance, to drink thereof morning and Evening, and abſtaining from other drink two or three houres after; it is often uſed as a ſpecial remedy againſt the ſtone and other pains of the bowels. The Decoction thereof with Succory and Centory, is held very effectual to help the Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and them that are inclining thereto, and the diſeaſes of the Spleen: It ſtayeth the Fluxes of blood either at the mouth or noſe, and inward bleedings alſo, for it is a ſingular wound herb. It help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the bloody Flix, and ſtayeth the abundance of womens Courſes. The Juice or Decoction of the herb taken before the fit of a Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane Ague, is ſaid to keep back or much to leſſen the fit, and by the uſe of it to take it quite away. It is good for Ruptures or burſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. The diſtilled water thereof is available in all the diſeaſes aforeſaid. The ſyrupe made thereof is uſeful for ſuch as are troubled with the Cough and Conſumption, as alſo for inward bleedings and Ruptures.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The manner of Adminiſtering it.</head>
                  <p>It is given in Juice, Decoction or Powder.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The green herb bruiſed, and preſently bound to any freſh cut or wound, doth quickly ſodder the lips thereof; and the Juice, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction or Powder of the dried herb is moſt ſingular to ſtay the malignitie of ſpreading or fretting Cankers or Vlcers. Whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, as well thoſe in the mouth, as ſecret parts of Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. The diſtilled water is good to waſh wounds and ſores, and to apply Tents or clothes wet therein. The Powder of the drie herb,
<pb facs="tcp:118548:17"/>
ſtayeth bleeding at the noſe, being put therein. It is ſaid to be ſo powerful to harden iron or ſteele, that if any edged or pointed tool ſhall be often quenched in the juice thereof, it will cut all other iron, or ſteel, or ſtone very eaſily, without turning edge or point.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Doſe.</head>
                  <p>It is given in powder from half a dram to a dram, in juice from one ſpoonful to two.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch Medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled Water. The Syrupe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 27. Of <hi>Nep.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called <hi>Nepeta, Herba Cattania,</hi> and <hi>Herba Catti,</hi> and that becauſe Cats delight both to ſmel and eat thereof and gladly rub themſelves againſt it. It is hot and drie in the third Degree, and of thinne parts.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Duration.</head>
                  <p>It will keep good a yeare.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>It is uſed to procure Womens Courſes, it warmeth and comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the coldneſſe, and drieth the over-much moiſture of the mother, which may be the cauſe of barrenneſſe, and by the frequent uſe of it may cauſe women to be more fruitful. It is alſo good for the wind, and pains of the mother or riſing of it. It is uſed in pains of the head that come from any cold cauſe, as Catarrhes and thinne Rheumes, and for giddineſſe thereof, and for winds in the ſtomach and belly; alſo for cramps or cold aches to diſſolve the cold and winde that affecteth the place, and to bring warmth and comfort thereunto af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards. It is uſed for colds and coughs, and ſhortneſſe of breath. The juice thereof drunk in Wine is profitable for thoſe that are bruiſed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118548:17"/>
                  <head>The manner of Adminiſtring.</head>
                  <p>It is chiefly given in Decoction.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>A bath made thereof and uſed, or to ſit over the hot Fumes, doth help to bring down womens Courſes, help barrenneſſe, and warm thoſe parts. The green herb bruiſed and applied to the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dament there abiding for two or three houres, eaſeth the ſharp pains of the piles, the juice alſo is effectual for the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, being made up into an Ointment and applied. A Decocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof is commended to waſh the head, to take away the ſcabs thereof, and may be effectual for other parts of the body alſo.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 28. Of <hi>Onions.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperaments.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine, <hi>Cepa;</hi> in Engliſh, Onions. They are hot and drie in the fourth Degree.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>Onions provoke the appetite, eaſe the pains of the belly, provoke urine and womens Courſes, help the biting of a mad Dog, and of other venemous creatures, to be uſed with a little Honey and Rue, and increaſe Sperme, eſpecially the ſeed. They alſo kill the worms in children if they drink the water faſting wherein they have been ſteeped all night: being roſted under the Embers, and eaten with Honey and Sugar, and Oyle, they help an old Cough, by cutting the tough Flegme and cauſing it to be eaſily ſpit forth. It is coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by many a good preſervative againſt infection, to eat Onions faſting with bread and ſalt. Onions ſliced and dipped in the juice of Sorrel, and given to one ſick of a Tertian Ague, to eat, taketh away the fit in once or twiſe ſo taking them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The manner of Adminiſtering them.</head>
                  <p>The beſt way to uſe them is to boyl them, and ſo to eat them with Butter, Vinegar and Pepper, or to lay them a ſteep ſome time in water, and ſo to eat them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118548:18"/>
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The juice ſnuffed up into the noſtrils, purgeth the head, and help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Lethargie, and is good alſo for ſcalding or burning by fire, water or gunpowder, and uſed with Vinegar taketh away all ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes, ſpots and marks in the skinne, and dropped into the eares, eaſeth the pains and noiſe in them: applyed alſo with Figs beaten together helpeth to ripen and break Impoſtumes and other ſores, eſpecially being firſt roſted in Embers, ſtamped with Salt, Rue, and Hony, and ſo applied, they are good againſt the biting of a mad Dog. The juice of Onions mixed with the Decoction of Penni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial, and a cloth wet therein and applied, eaſeth the Gout. Some take a great Onion, and being made hollow, they fill the place with good Treacle, and then roaſt it well under Embers, after which let the outermoſt skins be taken away, and being well beaten and applied to any Plague ſore, or putrid ulcer, they ſay it is a ſoveraign Medicine. The juice mixed with Hony, and a bald head anointed therewith cauſeth the hair to grow again. They provoke the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrhoides being laid unto them, either by themſelves or ſtamped with Vinegar. They help Kibes being roaſted and applied with but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or hogs-greaſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The hurtful qualitie.</head>
                  <p>Being too often or immoderately eaten raw, they breed ill and corrupt humours in the ſtomach, inflame the blood, increaſe thirſt, cauſe drowſineſſe and the head-ache, hurt the ſight, dull and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb the memorie and underſtanding. They are hurtful to young men and chollerick perſons. They are flatulent or windie.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 29. Of <hi>Oſmund royal.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine <hi>Oſmunda regalis,</hi> of the ſingular properties therein, alſo <hi>Filix aquatica;</hi> in Engliſh, Oſmund royal, Oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund the waterman, water Fern and Zut. <hi>Chriſtophers herb.</hi> The root is hot and drie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118548:18"/>
                  <head>The Duration.</head>
                  <p>The root will keep good two or three years,</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The Decoction of the leaves or roots drunk, is uſeful for Ruptures or burſtings, as alſo for ſuch as have falled or bruiſed themſelves, or have any inward wound, and giveth eaſe to the Collick and ſplene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick diſeaſes. The powder hath the ſams vertue, and is excellent for ſuch as cannot hold their water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The manner of Administring it.</head>
                  <p>It is given in Decoction or powder.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>It is ſingular in wounds, bruiſes, broken bones, Ruptures or burſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, boyled into an Ointment or Oyle as a Balſame or Balme, or boyled in aſtringent wine, and ſo applied in manner of a Poultis.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Doſe.</head>
                  <p>The Doſe of the root in powder, is from half a ſcruple to two ſcruples.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch Medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled water of the leaves, Syrupe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 30. Of <hi>Parſley.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine, <hi>Petroſelinum;</hi> in Engliſh, Parſley, or garden Parſley. It is hot and dry in the ſecond Degree, the ſeed hot in the ſecond Degree, and drie almoſt in the third: the root is alſo of a moderate heat.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>It is much uſed in meats and brothes in all Countries, and doth help to provoke Urine, and Womens Courſes, and to break wind both in the ſtomach and bowels, and doth a little open the body,
<pb facs="tcp:118548:19"/>
but the root much more, and openeth the ſtoppings of both Liver and Spleen, and is profitable for the yellow Jaundiſe, and Dropſie, <hi>Galen</hi> commendeth it againſt the Falling-ſickneſſe, and to provoke Urine mightily, eſpecially if the roots be boyled and eaten with Parſneps. The ſeed is held by moſt to be moſt effectual, yet ſome do think the root to be ſtrongeſt: but the ſeed is effectual to provok Vrine and Womens Courſes, to expel winds, to breake the ſtone, and to eaſe the pains and torments thereof, or of any other part in the ſtomach and body procured by wind, and alſo is effectual againſt venome, and is put therefore into counterpoyſons for that purpoſe as alſo againſt the danger that cometh to them that have taken Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharge; it is alſo uſed among other things, that ſerve for the Cough. The ſeeds boyled in white wine and taken help to bring away the Birth and after Birth. The diſtilled water of the herb is much uſed by Nurſes for Children againſt wind and gripings in the belly or ſtomach.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The manner of adminiſtering it.</head>
                  <p>It is chiefly uſed in Decoction.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Decoction againſt the Jaundiſe, Dropſie, Falling-ſickneſſe, Stone in the Reins.</head>
                  <p>Take of Parſly ſeeds, Fennel, Aniſeed and Carrawayes of each an Ounce of the roots of Parſly, Burnet, Saxi frage and Carrawayes, of each one Ounce and a half: let the ſeeds be bruiſed and the roots waſhed and cut ſmall, let them all be ſteeped in a pottle of white wine one night, and in the morning boyled in a cloſe earthen veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel until a third part or more be waſted, which being ſtrained and cleared, take foure Ounces thereof at a time, morning and evening firſt and laſt abſtaining from drink for three houres after.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The leaves of Parſly laid to the eyes that are inflamed with heate or are ſwollen doth much help them, if it be uſed with bread or meal: and being laid to womens hard breaſts that come by the curd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their milk, doth abate the hardneſſe quickly, if it be fried with butter and applied, and doth alſo take away black and blew ſpats or marks by bruiſes, fals, &amp;c, The juice thereof dropped into the ears with a little wine eaſeth the pains thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118548:19"/>
                  <head>The hurtfull qualitie.</head>
                  <p>Parſly eaten raw and too frequently, hurts the head, breedeth cholerick blood, and is hardly digeſted. Women with child muſt not be too bold with it leaſt it prove dangerous to them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch Medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled water.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 31. Of <hi>Pellitorie</hi> of the wall.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine, <hi>Helxine</hi> and <hi>Perdicium,</hi> becauſe Partridges ſometimes feed thereon; alſo <hi>Parietaria</hi> and <hi>herba Muralis,</hi> or <hi>Muralium,</hi> becauſe it groweth near to walls. It is counted by moſt to be cold and moiſt, but ſurely it is hot, otherwiſe it cannot be ſo effectual againſt wind and the ſtone.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Duration.</head>
                  <p>It will keep good a year.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The dried herb in powder made up with Hony into an Electuarie, or the juice of the herb, or the Decoction thereof taken with Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar or Honie, is a ſingular remedy for any old continual, or drie cough, ſhortneſſe of breath, and wheeſing in the throat: the juice thereof taken to the quantitie of three ounces at a time doth won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully eaſe thoſe that are troubled with the ſuppreſſion of their Vrine, and to expel both the gravel and ſtone. The Decoction alſo of the herb being drunk, eaſeth the pains of the mother, and provoketh the Courſes; the ſame alſo eaſeth thoſe griefs that ariſe from the ſtoppings of the Liver, Spleen and Reins. The diſtilled water drunken with Sugar worketh the ſame effects.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The manner of Adminiſtring it.</head>
                  <p>It is chiefly uſed in Decoction.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118548:20"/>
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>It is much uſed in Glyſters to eaſe pains in the back, ſides or bowels proceeding from wind, or the like ſtoppings of Urine, or the gravel and ſtone: it worketh the like effect alſo, if the bruiſed herb ſprinkled with ſome Muskadine be warmed upon a tile, or in a diſh upon a few quick coals in a chaffing-diſh, and applied to the belly. The decoction thereof may ſerve as a bath for women to ſit in to bring down their Courſes, to eaſe gripings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The ſame Decoction alſo with a little Hony added thereto will ſerve to good purpoſe to gargle the throat when it is ſwollen or pained. The juice held a while in the mouth eaſeth the tooth-ache, and dropped into the ears, eaſeth the noiſe and hummings in them, and taketh away the pricking and ſhooting pains in them. The juice, or herb bruiſed and applied with a little ſalt is very effectual to cleanſe Fiſtulaes and to heal them. It is likewiſe very effectual for any green wound that if it be bruiſed and bound thereto for three dayes you need no other medicine or ſalve to heal it. A Pultis made hereof with Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, and boyled in Wine with Wheat bran and Bean flower, and ſome Oyle put thereto, and applied warm to any bruiſed Sinew, Tendon, or Muscle, doth in a very ſhort time reſtore them to their ſtrength, and taketh away the pains of bruiſes, and diſſolveth the congealed blood of any beatings, or fals from high places. The juice or the diſtilled water cleanſeth the skinne from Spots, Freckles, Purples, Wheals, Sunburn, Morphew, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and leaveth the skin ſmooth and delicate. The ſaid Water or Juice, doth aſſwage hot Impoſtumes, burnings or ſcaldings, as alſo all other hot tumours or inflammations, be it Saint <hi>Anthonies</hi> fire, or any other eruptions of heat, being bathed often with wet clothes dipped therein; or the ſaid juice made into an Ointment with Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſſe and Oyle of Roſes, and annointed therewith, which doth alſo cleanſe foule rotten Ulcers, and ſtayeth creeping Ulcers, and run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Scabs in Childrens heads, and helpeth alſo to ſtay the falling off the hair of the head, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The leaves mixed with Oyle of ſweet Almonds in manner of a Pultis, and laid to the pained parts, is a good help for them that are troubled with the Stone, or are trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with Wind and gripings.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118548:20"/>
                  <head>Of ſuch Medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled Water.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 32. Of <hi>Penny-royal.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine, <hi>Pulegium,</hi> becauſe it killeth fleas being burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; In Engliſh, Penny-royal, and Pudding-graſſe. It is hot and dry in the third Degree, and of ſubtile parts.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Duration.</head>
                  <p>It will keep good a year.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>It maketh thick flegm thinn, warmeth a cold ſtomach, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſteth raw matter, being boyled and drunk; it provoketh wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Courſes, expels the dead child and after Birth, and allayeth the gnawing of the ſtomach. Being mixed with Honey and ſalt and drunk, it is a good Medicine for the Lungs, and helpeth cramps. The Decoction thereof is good in the Falling-ſickneſſe, Dropſie, Jaundiſe, ſtopping of the Vrine, and in the Leproſie. Drunk with wine, it helpeth ſuch as are ſtung with venemous beaſts.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The manner of adminiſtering it.</head>
                  <p>It is chiefly uſed in Decoction.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>Applied to the noſtrils with Vinegar, it reviveth thoſe that are fainting or ſounding: being dried and burnt it ſtrengthneth the gums. It is helpful to thoſe that are troubled with the gout applied to the place till it wax red: applied in a cerot or plaiſter, it taketh away ſpots or marks in the face; it much profiteth thoſe that are ſplenetick or liver grown being applied with ſalt. The Decoction helpeth thoſe that have the itch, being bathed therewith: being put into baths for women to ſit therein, it helpeth the ſwelling and hardneſſe of the mother, and when it is out of its place. Being brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and put into Vinegar it cleanſeth foul Vlcers, and cauſeth the
<pb facs="tcp:118548:21"/>
matter to digeſt; it helpeth black and blew eyes and all diſcolour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the face by the fire. Being boyled in wine with Hony and Salt, it helpeth the tooth-ache. It helpeth the cold griefs of the joynts, taking away the pains and warming the cold parts, being faſt bound to the place after a bathing, or having been in a hot houſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A lotion to refreſh wearied limbs.</head>
                  <p>Take of Penny-royal and Origanum of each a handful and a half, of Sage a handful. Boyl them in water, and waſh therewith or bath therein at night.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The hurtful qualitie.</head>
                  <p>Very hot and drie bodies muſt not be too buſie with it:</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch Medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled water, Conſerve, Oyle Chymical.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 33. Of <hi>Periwinkle.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine, <hi>Vinca Pervinca,</hi> and <hi>Pervinca,</hi> alſo <hi>Clema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Pervinca;</hi> in Engliſh, Periwinkle, and Pervinkle, It is hot about the ſecond Degree, ſomething drie and aſtringent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The leaves boyled in wine and drunk, ſtoppeth the lask and bloody flix. An handful of the leaves ſtamped, and the juice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of given to drink in red wine ſtoppeth the lask and bloody flix, ſpit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of blood, the bleeding of the Hemorrhoides, and the overflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of womens Courſes, which ſeldome faileth in any. It is alſo excellent in inward wounds.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The manner of Adminiſtring it.</head>
                  <p>It is given in juice, or in Decoction.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The juice or the herb bruiſed, and put into the noſe, ſtoppeth the bleeding thereof. The ſame chewed helpeth the tooth-ache, and all ſtinging of venemous beaſts being thereto applied. The ſame mingled with milk and oyl of Roſes and put into the Matrix in a Peſſary or in other Suppoſitory, taketh away the pains thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118548:21"/>
                  <head>Of ſuch Medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled Water.</p>
                  <p>Pilewort, See Celandine.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 34. Of garden and wild <hi>Poppies.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>THe white Poppy is called in Latine, <hi>Papaver album ſativum,</hi> the black, <hi>Papaver nigrum ſativum;</hi> the red, <hi>Papaver rubrum ſativum;</hi> the red wild Poppie is called <hi>Papaver Rhaeas, Papaver er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raticum,</hi> and <hi>Sylveſtre,</hi> in Engliſh, Red Poppy and Corn-Roſe. They are all cold and moiſt, ſome in the third, ſome in the fourth Degree.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>They are chiefly in uſe to cauſe ſleep, to cool the body, and alſo in diſeaſes of the breaſt and lungs, eſpecially in the Cough, Hoarſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and Conſumptions of the Lungs. The Garden Poppy heads with ſeeds made into a ſyrupe, is frequently uſed to procure reſt and ſleep, in the ſick and weak, and to ſtay hot Rheumes that fall from the head into the ſtomach, and upon the lungs, cauſing a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Cough, the fore-runner of a Conſumption: the ſame alſo helpeth the hoarſneſſe of the throat, and when one hath loſt their voice, which the oyl of the ſeed doth likewiſe. The black ſeed boyled in wine and drunk is ſaid to ſtay the flux of the belly, and the immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Courſes of women. The empty ſhels, or husks of the Poppy heads, are uſualy boiled in water, and given to procure ſleep; ſo do the leavs in the ſame manner, A caudle made of the ſeeds of white Poppy or made into Almond milk, and ſo given cauſeth ſleep. The wild or red Poppy that groweth in the Corn, while it is young, is a ſallet herb in Italy in many places, and is uſed to prevent the Falling-ſickneſſe. The Syrupe made with the Flowers is given to thoſe that have a Pleuriſie, and the dried flowers alſo, either boyled in water, or made into Powder, and drunke either in the diſtilled water of them, or in ſome other drink, worketh the like effects, and is good alſo in all other diſeaſes of the head and breſt. The diſtilled water thereof is uſed againſt ſurfets, to drink it evening and morning. It is
<pb facs="tcp:118548:22"/>
more cooling then other Poppies, and therefore cannot but be as effectual in hot Agues, Frenſies and other inflammations, the Syrupe or water to be uſed. Concerning <hi>Opium</hi> which is the juice of Pop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie thickned; ſee my firſt part of the nature of Simple Medicines, Chap. 49.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The manner of Adminiſtering it.</head>
                  <p>It is uſed in Decoction, Syrupe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>A Decoction of the leaves provoketh reſt, if the temples and head or feet be bathed therewith, and the Oyle doth the like. The green heads or leaves bruiſed and applied with a little Vinegar or made into a Pultis with Barley meal and Hogs greaſe, cooleth all inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, as alſo that diſeaſe called Saint <hi>Anthonies</hi> fire.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The hurtfull Qualitie.</head>
                  <p>It muſt not be uſed in cold and moiſt bodies, nor to ſuch as have the Palſie, Cramp, Lethargy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch Medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled water, Syrupe, both ſimple and compound of many kinds. <hi>Ex tract. Lohoch</hi> Oyle.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 35. Of <hi>Quinces.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>TThe Quince is called in Latine, <hi>malus Cydonia,</hi> and <hi>Cotonea;</hi> bccauſe they were firſt brought out of Candy, ſaith <hi>Plinie</hi> in his Natural Hiſtorie, Book 15. Chap. 11. page 436. <hi>Malum Coto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neum, Pomum Cydonium,</hi> and many times <hi>Cydonium</hi> without any addition, are other names given to it. They are cold in the firſt, and drie in the ſecond Degree, and very binding. The ſweet are not ſo cold nor binding as the ſowre.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>They are good to ſtay all manner of fluxes in man or woman, and chollerick lasks, caſtings, and whatſoever needeth binding, and
<pb facs="tcp:118548:22"/>
that more when they are green, then any way prepared by fire. The Syrupe made of the juice is very profitable for the ſame alſo, ſo is the Conſerve: If a little Vinegar be added, it ſtirreth up the weak appetite, and the ſtomach given to caſting, and if ſome ſpices be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, it comforteth and ſtrengthneth the decaying and fainting ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and helpeth the Liver oppreſt, that it cannot perfect the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion, and correcteth choller and flegme. To take of the raw juice of Quinces, is held a preſervative againſt the force of deadly poyſon. They are good for thoſe that ſpit up blood, or vomit blood, or for the Hicket. The Muſſilage of the ſeed taken with a little Sugar is good for the harſhneſſe and hoarſneſſe of the throat, and roughneſſe of the tongue. Quinces uſed before meals bind the belly, but eaten after meals they looſe the belly.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The manner of Adminiſtring them.</head>
                  <p>They muſt not be eaten raw, but either roaſted, baked, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The ſmell of Quince taketh away the ſtrength of the poyſon of white Hellebore, which Hunters make to kill wild beaſts by dipping their Arrow heads therein: It hath alſo been found certain, that if Quinces be brought into a houſe where Grapes are hung up to be kept drie all the year, they will aſſuredly rot with the very ſmell of them. If there be need of any outward binding and cooling of any hot fluxes, the Oyle of Quinces, or the other Medicines that may be made thereof, are very available to anoint the belly or other parts therewith, it likewiſe ſtrengtheneth the ſtomach and belly, and the ſinewes that are looſened by ſharp humours falling on them, and reſtraineth immoderate ſweatings. The muſſilage of the ſeeds made in water is very good to cool the heat, heal the ſore breaſts of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. The Cotton or Downe of Quinces boyled in wine and applied to plague ſores, healeth them up, and laid as a plaiſter made up with wax, it bringeth haire to them that are bald, and keepeth it from falling, if it be ready to ſhed. The ſeeds are very uſeful in Gliſters againſt fluxes of the belly.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The hurtfull qualitie.</head>
                  <p>Quinces are not convenient for ſuch as are much troubled with coſtiveneſſe, or much bound in their bodies.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118548:23"/>
                  <head>Of ſuch Medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>Syrupe of divers kinds both ſimple and compound, Marmalade, Preſerved Quinces, Rob <hi>Cydoniorum,</hi> Eſſence or Spirit, Oyle. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 36. Of <hi>Sage</hi> of Jeruſalem.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine, <hi>Pulmonaria,</hi> and <hi>Pulmonaria maculoſa</hi> to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh it from the other Lungwort; alſo <hi>Symphitum maculo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum;</hi> in Engliſh, Sage of Jeruſalem, Couſlip of Jeruſalem, Sage of Bethlehem, Lungwort and ſpotted Comfrey. It is judged by ſome to be cold and drie, by others to be hot and dry.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>It is chiefly commended in the Cough, ſhortneſſe of breath, in ulcers of the Lungs, and for ſuch as are full of rotten matter, and alſo for ſuch as ſpit blood, being boyled in water and drunk. It is a very good Pot-herb, and much in uſe for that purpoſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The manner of Adminiſtering it.</head>
                  <p>It is chiefly uſed in Decoction.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>It is uſed to heal old or new wounds, being thereto applied, or boyled in Hogs-greaſe, ſtrained, and being cold laid thereto.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch Medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled water.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 37. Of <hi>Sanicle,</hi> or <hi>Sanickle.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine, <hi>Sanicula,</hi> from its excellencie in healing wounds, alſo <hi>Diapenſia;</hi> in Engliſh Sanicle, and Sanickle. It is
<pb facs="tcp:118548:23"/>
hot and drie in the ſecond Degree, and bitter and aſtringent, or binding.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Duration.</head>
                  <p>It will keep good a year.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>It helpeth Wounds, Ulcers, Impoſtumes, or any inward bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and doth wonderfully help thoſe that have any tumour in their bodies in any part, if the Decoction or juice thereof be taken, or the powder in drink; for there is not found any herb that can give ſuch preſent help, either to man or beaſt, when the diſeaſe falleth upon the lungs or throat. It ſtayeth all womens Courſes, and all other fluxes of blood, either by the mouth, urine or ſtool, and lasks of the belly, the ulceration of the kidneyes alſo, and the pains in the bowels, and the running of the reins, being boyled in water and drunk: the ſame helpeth ruptures or burſtings, and is as effectual in binding, reſtraining, conſolidating, heating, drying and healing, as Comfrey, Bugle. Self heal, or any other woundherb whatſoever. A ſpoonful or two of the juice taken three or foure mornings toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a little Sugar helpeth ſuch as have any veine broken in the lungs, or ſpetting of blood.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The manner of Administring it.</head>
                  <p>It is chiefly uſed in Decoction.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>It cureth all green Wounds and Ulcers ſpeedily if they be waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Decoction thereof, or the juice. It healeth alſo all malign, putrid, or ſtinking ulcers of the mouth, throat and privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, by gargling or waſhing with the Decoction of the leaves and roots made in water, and a little Honey put thereto. The herb boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in water and applied in manner of a Pultis, doth diſſolve and waſt away cold ſwellings,</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The hurtfull qualitie.</head>
                  <p>Such as are much bound in their bodies are not to uſe it too fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch things as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled water of the green herb, The juice.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:118548:24"/>
               <head>CHAP. 38. Of <hi>Savine.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine <hi>Sabina,</hi> and <hi>Savina;</hi> in Engliſh Savine, or garden Savine. It is hot and drie in the third Degree.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Duration.</head>
                  <p>It will keep good a year, but you may have it green all the year. It is hot and drie in the third Degree.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Matthiolus</hi> ſaith, that a dram of Savine in powder mixt with 3 oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Niter, and 2 of Hony doth wonderfully help ſuch as are ſhort winded. The Decoction thereof drunk, doth provoke the courſes, and draweth forth the Birth and after Birth, expelleth blood by urine, and is profitable for the Kings Evil. It killeth worms in chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and the Bots in Horſes or Cattel, to give it in their drink, or with their Oats. The diſtilled water thereof is effectual againſt worms, and helpeth thoſe that have a giddineſſe in their brain. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine doth powerfully reſiſt putrifactions.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The manner of Adminiſtring.</head>
                  <p>It is given in Decoction, or in Powder.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The perfume of the Decoction taken underneath, provoketh the Courſes, brings away the Birth and after Birth. Being mixed with Hony and uſed; it cures Vlcers, ſtayeth ſpreading and creeping Vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, taketh away their blackneſſe, as alſo all ſpots and freckles from the face or body. It breaketh or diſſolveth Carbuncles and Plague ſores. It killed worms being boyled and applied to the belly, or the Oyle made thereof and uſed doth the like. The powder of the leaves mixed with cream, or the green leaves boyled in cream, and anointed on running ſores, or dry ſores, cleanſeth them through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and healeth them, as alſo Saint <hi>Anthonies</hi> fire. The freſh leaves bruiſed and laid upon running and fretting Cankers and the like, killeth and deſtroyeth them. The powder of the leaves uſed with ſome other things, or ſtrewed upon doth help thoſe bliſters that
<pb facs="tcp:118548:24"/>
riſe on the yard by inordinate luxurie, after they have been bathed with the Decoction of the leaves. The diſtilled water doth cleanſe the skin from ſpots of marks therein, and other deformities. The ſmoake thereof cureth Hens that have gotten the pipp.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The hurtful qualitie.</head>
                  <p>It muſt not be given to women with childe but with good adviſe, leaſt it deſtroy the Birth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch things as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled water. The Oyle of Savine.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 39. Of <hi>Savorie.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Kinds, Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>THere are two ſorts of Savory chiefly in uſe; the Winter and the Summer Savory: The Winter Savory is called <hi>Satureia hortenſis,</hi> or <hi>vulgaris,</hi> the Summer Savory is called <hi>Satureia horten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis activa.</hi> Both ſorts are hot and dry in the third Degree, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the Summer kind, which is both ſharp and quicke in taſte:</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>Savory expelleth wind in the ſtomach and bowels, and is a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent help for the riſing of the mother procured by wind, provoketh Vrine and womens Courſes, and is much commended for women with childe to take often of it, It procures a good appetite to meat and takes away all manner of loathing to the ſame. It cutteth tough flegme in the cheſt and lungs, and helpeth to bring it away more eaſily. It quickneth the ſight, and ſome write that it provok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth venery.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>It is much commended for women with childe to ſmel often to it. It helpeth to quicken the dull ſpirits of the Lethargy, the juice being ſnuffed up into the noſtrils: the juice alſo is of good uſe to be dropped into the eyes to clear the dull ſight, if it proceed of raw thinn cold humours diſtilling from the brain. The ſame alſo heated
<pb facs="tcp:118548:25"/>
with a little Oyle of Roſes, and dropped into the ears, taketh away the noiſe and ſinging in them, and deafneſſe alſo. Being applied with wheat flower in manner of a Poultis, giveth eaſe to the Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atica, or members that have the Palſie by heating and warming them, and taketh away the pain. It taketh away the ſtinging of Bees, Waſps, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and being laid in Chambers it killeth Fleas.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch things as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled water, Chymical Oyle.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 40. Of Engliſh or common <hi>Saxifrage.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperaments.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine <hi>Saxifraga,</hi> and <hi>Saxifraga Anglicana,</hi> in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, Stone-break and Engliſh Saxifrage. It is hot and dry in the third Degree.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Duration.</head>
                  <p>It will keep good a year.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>A Decoction made with the ſeeds and roots being taken, break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ſtone in the bladder and kidneyes, helpeth the ſtrangury, and cauſeth one to piſſe freely. The roots boyled in Wine, and taken, bringeth down womens Courſes, expelleth the after Birth and dead Child. The root dried and made into powder, and taken with Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, comforteth and warmeth the ſtomach, cureth the gnawings and griping pains of the belly, eaſeth the Collick alſo, and expelleth wind.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Cheſhire-women</hi> put it in their running or rennet for cheeſe. The diſtilled water is much in uſe to give children againſt the ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of their Urine, and to eaſe griping pains in their belly.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The manner of Adminiſtring it.</head>
                  <p>It is uſed chiefly in Decoction.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118548:25"/>
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>It is uſed outwardly in Bathes and Fomentations to provoke Vrine and to eaſe pains of the belly <hi>&amp;c.</hi> proceeding from wind.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Doſe.</head>
                  <p>It is given from half a dram to a dram, both the root, herb and ſeeds.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch Medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled water.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 41. Of <hi>Scabious.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine, <hi>Scabioſa;</hi> in Engliſh Scabious. It is hot and dry in the ſecond Degree, opening, cleanſing, digeſting, and making thinne.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Duration.</head>
                  <p>It will keep good a year.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>It is effectual for all ſorts of Coughs, ſhortneſſe of breath, and all other the diſeaſes of the breſt and lungs, ripening and digeſting cold flegme, and other tough humours, voyding them forth by cough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſpitting. It ripeneth alſo all ſort of inward Vlcers and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtumes, yea the Pleuriſie alſo, if the Decoction of the dry or green herb being made with wine be drunk ſome time together, thereby voiding it forth by Vrine, as well as other wayes. Four ounces of the clarified juice of Scabious taken in the morning faſting, with a dram of Mithridate or Venice Treacle, doth free the heart from any infection of the Plague or Peſtilence, ſo as upon the taking thereof they ſweat two houres in their beds at the firſt, yet after the firſt time taking, let them that are infected take the ſame proportion again, and again if need be, for fear of further danger. The ſame is good againſt the ſtinging of any venemous beaſt. The Decoction drunke helpeth the pains and ſtitches of the ſides, The Decoction of the roots taken for fourtie dayes together, or the powder of them to the quantity of a dramme at a time, taken in Whey, doth
<pb facs="tcp:118548:26"/>
as <hi>Matthiolus</hi> ſaith, wonderfully help thoſe that are troubled with dangerous running or ſpreading Scabs, Tetters, or Ringworms, yea although they proceed from the French pox. The juice or the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction drunk doth very much help thoſe that are broken out into ſcabs and itches. The ſame alſo wonderfully helpeth all inward wounds, be they made by thruſt or ſtroke, by the drying, cleanſing, and healing qualitie therein. A Syrupe made of the juice and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, is very effectual to all the purpoſes aforeſaid, and ſo is the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilled water of the herb and flowers made in due time.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The manner of Adminiſtring it.</head>
                  <p>It is given in Decoction chiefly.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Decoction, good againſt the Cough and ſhoreneſſe of breath, &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>Take of dried Scabious a handful, Licoris bruiſed, Anniſeed and Fennelſeed bruiſed, of each one Ounce, white Orris root cut in thin ſlices half an Ounce Figs cut into pieces a dozen: Let all be ſteeped for a night, in a quart of fair water (or rather in ſo much wine) boyling them the next day, until a third part be conſumed at the leaſt, whereof take a draught every morning and evening warm, with Hony or Sugar.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The green herb bruiſed and applied to any Carbuncle or Plague ſore is found by good experience to diſſolve or break it within the ſpace of three houres; the ſame applied helpeth the ſtinging of any venemous beaſt. The juice made up into an ointment with Hogs-greaſe helpeth the itch and ſcab, being thereto applied. The Deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the herb and roots applied, doth help all ſorts of hard or cold tumours, or ſwellings in any part of the body; and is alſo as effectual for any ſhrunk ſinew or veine in any place. The juice made up with the powder of Borax and Camphor, doth cleanſe the skin of the face, or any other part of the body, as Freckles, Pimples, Morphew and Leprie. The ſame Decoction helpeth the redneſſe and ſpots in the white of the eyes, uſed either by it ſelf, or with the juice of Fennel. The head waſhed with the ſame Decoction, cleanſeth it from dandraffe, ſcurff, ſcabs, ſores, itches and the like, being uſed warm; Tents alſo dipped in the juice or water thereof, doth heale all green wounds, old ſores and ulcers. The herb bruiſed
<pb facs="tcp:118548:26"/>
and applied, doth looſen ſplinter, broken bone, arrow head, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch like thing lying in the fleſh, and cauſeth it to be eaſily drawn forth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch things as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled water. Syrup both ſimple and compound. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve of the flowers. Salt.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 42. Of <hi>Scurvy-graſſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>THe common Scurvy-graſſe is called <hi>Cochlearia,</hi> and <hi>Cochlearia vulgaris;</hi> the other ſort with round leaves is called in Latine, <hi>Cochlearia rotundifolia,</hi> and <hi>Cochlearia Batava;</hi> in Engliſh, Scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigraſſe, or Spoonwort, that with round leaves is called Dutch-Scutvy-graſſe. Its hot and dry in the ſecond or third Degree, eſpecially the garden Scurvy-graſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The Engliſh Scurvy-graſſe is more uſed for the ſalt taſt it bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, which doth ſomewhat open and cleanſe, but the Dutch or gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Scurvy-graſſe is of better effect, and chiefly uſed (if it may be had) by thoſe that have the Scurvy, eſpecially alſo to purge and cleanſe the Blood, the Liver and Spleen; for all which diſeaſes it is of ſingular good effect, by taking the juice in the Spring every morning faſting in a cup of drink. The Decoction is good for the ſame purpoſe, and the herb tunned up in new drink either by it ſelf or with other things, for it openeth obſtructions or ſtoppings and evacuateth cold clammy and flegmatick humours both from the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and Spleen, waſting and conſuming the ſwelling and hardneſſe thereof, and thereby bringing to the body a more lively co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour. The Conſerve made of the leaves is a fine delicate Medicine for weak and tender ſtomachs, and worketh the ſame effect, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though a little ſlowly; the like doth the Syrupe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The manner of Adminiſtering it.</head>
                  <p>It is given in juice, Decoction, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118548:27"/>
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The Juice helpeth all foul Vlcers and ſores in the mouth, if it be often gargled therewith, and uſed to the skin doth cleanſe the ſame from ſpots, marks or skars that happeneth therein.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch Medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled Water; Syrupe, Conſerve, Salt, and Spirit of Scurvy-graſſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sengreen,</hi> See <hi>Houſe-leek.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 43. Of <hi>Shepheards purſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine, <hi>Burſa paſtoris,</hi> or <hi>Pera paſtoris;</hi> in Engliſh, ſhepheards purſe or pouch, and in the North, Pick-purſe and Caſe-weed. It is counted by moſt to be cold and dry, and much binding.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Duration.</head>
                  <p>It will keep good a year.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>It ſtayeth all fluxes of blood, as alſo the fluxes of the belly, the bloody flux and the abundance of womens Courſes, or the piſſing of blood, the juice or the Decoction of the herb with ſome Plantane being drunk, or any other way taken.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The manner of Adminiſtering it.</head>
                  <p>It is chiefly given in Decoction.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>In a Gliſter it cureth the bloody flix, and bruiſed and applied it helpeth inflammations, and Saint <hi>Anthonies</hi> fire, cureth green wounds, and is of great effect being made into a Salve for wounds in the head. It ſtayeth the bleeding of the noſe, or any wound bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, being thereto applied. Some hold that the green herb bruiſed and bound to the wreſts of the hands, and ſoles of the feet, will help the yellow Jaundiſe, and mitigate the fits of Agues.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118548:27"/>
                  <head>Of ſuch Medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled water.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 44. Of <hi>Smallage.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine, <hi>Apium, Apium paluſtre</hi> and <hi>Paludapium;</hi> in Engliſh, Smallage and water Parſly. It is hote and drie neere in the third Degree.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>It openeth the ſtoppings of the Liver and Spleen, maketh thin thick fiegme, and cleanſeth it and the blood withal. It provoketh Vrine and Womens Courſes, and is good for the yellow Jaundiſe, and for the tertian and quartain Agues, if the juice thereof be taken, but eſpecially made into a Syrupe. The ſeed is uſed to break and expel wind, to kill worms, and to help a ſtinking breath. The root is effectual for all the purpoſes aforeſaid, and is ſtronger in operation then the herb, but eſpecially to open ſtoppings, and to rid away an Ague, if the juice thereof be taken in wine, or the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction thereof in wine be taken. Pliny ſaith, it hath an eſpecial propertie againſt the poyſon of Spiders.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The juice put to hony of Roſes and ſome Barly water, is very good to gargle the mouth and throat of thoſe that have ſores and ulcers in them, and will quickly heal them: the ſame lotion alſo doth cleanſe and heal all other foul ulcers and cankers elſe where, if they be waſhed therewith. The leaves bruiſed and boyled with Hogs greaſe and made into a Poultis, cureth Felons and white flawes in the fingers, being thereto applied.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The hurtful qualitie.</head>
                  <p>It muſt not be uſed in very hot and dry bodies.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch Medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled water. Syrupe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:118548:28"/>
               <head>CHAP. 45. Of <hi>Sorrell.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine <hi>Oxlis</hi> of the ſharpe taſt, and <hi>Acetoſa,</hi> in Engliſh, Sorrell, and Garden Sorrel. It is cooling and drying in the ſecond Degree.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>It is prevalent in all hot diſeaſes to cool any inflammations, heat of the blood in Agues Peſtilential or Cholerick, or other ſickneſſes and faintings riſing from heat, and to refreſh the overſpent ſpirits with the violence of furious fits of Agues, &amp;c. to quench thirſt, and to procure an Appetite in fainting and decayed ſtomacks; for it reſiſteth the putrifaction of the blood, killeth wormes, and is as a Cordial to the heart, which the ſeed doth more effectually, being more drying and binding, and thereby alſo ſtayeth the hot fluxes of womens Courſes, or of humours in the bloody flix or flux of the ſtomach. The roots alſo in Decoction or in powder is effectual for the ſaid purpoſes: both roots and ſeeds, as well as the herb is held powerful to reſiſt the poyſon of the Scorpion, ſo that he that ſhall eat thereof, ſhall feel no pain being ſtung. The Decoction of the roots is taken to help the Iaundiſe, and to expel gravel and the ſtone in the Kidneyes. The Decoction of the Flowers made with wine, and drunk helpeth the black Jaundiſe, as alſo the inward ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the body or bowels. A Syrupe made with the Juice of Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel and Fumitorie is a ſoveraign help to kill the force of thoſe ſharp humours that cauſe the itch. The diſtilled water of the herb is uſed for the aforeſaid purpoſes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The juice with a little vinegar is uſeful for frettings and gallings of the skin in any part, and for Tetters, &amp;c. It helpeth alſo to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve or diſperſe kernels in the throat, and the juice gargled in the mouth helpeth the ſores therein, and dropped into the ears helpeth deafneſſe. The leaves wrapped up in a Colewort leafe, or a wet paper, and roaſted under the Embers, and applied to an hard impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtume, botch, bile or plague ſore, both ripeneth and breaketh it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118548:28"/>
                  <head>The hurtfull qualitie.</head>
                  <p>It is hurtful to melancholly perſons.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch Medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled water. Conſerve. Syrup.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 46. Of <hi>Spinage.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine, <hi>Spinachia</hi> and <hi>Spinacheum olus</hi> in Engliſh, Spinage and Spinach. It is cold and moiſt in the firſt or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Degree.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>Being young and tender it is uſed in Sallads, and looſeth the belly, moderately cooleth the Lungs, repreſſeth Choler, le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth the roughneſſe of the throat and wind-pipe, and is good for thoſe that have hot and chollerick ſtomachs. In <hi>France</hi> this herb ſhred and made up in bals, fried with Oyle and Vinegar, in the time of Lent, filleth up the room of an ordinary diſh.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>It is outwardly uſed to cool inflammations, to cool the heat of the ſtomach and Liver, and laid upon hot ſwellings, it taketh away the heat thereof, and diſſolveth the ſwelling.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The hurtful qualitie.</head>
                  <p>It weakneth the ſtomach, encreaſeth wind and wateriſh humours, and yieldeth little or no nouriſhment at all, hurteth the flegmatick, and being often uſed breeds melancholly blood.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch things as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled Water.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:118548:29"/>
               <head>CHAP. 47. Of <hi>Succory.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine, <hi>Cichorium</hi> and <hi>Cichorea,</hi> in Engliſh Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cory. It is cold and drie in the ſecond Degree, others will have it to be hot, becauſe it is bitter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>A handful of the leaves or roots boyled in wine or water, and a draught thereof drunk faſting driveth forth chollerick and flegma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick humours, openeth the ſtoppings of the Liver, Gall, and Spleen, helpeth the yellow Jaundiſe, the heat of the reins and of the urine, the Dropſie alſo, and thoſe that have the green ſickneſſe. A De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction thereof made with wine and drunk is very effectual againſt long lingering Agues; and a dram of the ſeed in powder drunk in wine before the fit of an Ague doth help to drive it away. The di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilled water of the herb and flowers performeth the ſame afore ſaid, and is ſpecial good for hot ſtomachs, and in Agues either pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilential, or of long continuance, and for ſwoundings and paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the heart, for the heat and head-ache in Children, and to temper the diſtemperature of the blood and liver.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The manner of Adminiſtering it.</head>
                  <p>It is uſed chiefly in Decoction, juice, and Syrupe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled water, or the juice, or the herb bruiſed and applied, allayeth tumours, inflammations, Saint <hi>Anthonies</hi> fire, puſhes, wheales and pimples, eſpecially uſed with a little Vinegar, as alſo to waſh peſtiferous ſores: the ſaid water is effectual for ſore eyes, that are inflamed or are red; as alſo for Nurſes ſore breaſts that are pained by abundance of milk.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch Medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled water. Conſerve. The root candied. Syrupe ſimple and compound.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:118548:29"/>
               <head>CHAP. 48. Of <hi>Tamarisk.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine <hi>Myrica Tamarix,</hi> and <hi>Tamariſcus;</hi> in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, Tamarisk. It is of a cleanſing and cutting quality, without manifeſt drying, that it hath a little therein, but the fruit and bark are much more drying.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Duration.</head>
                  <p>It will keep good a year, the bark longer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>It is very powerful againſt the ſtopping and hardneſſe of the Spleen, if the root or leaves, or young branches be boyled in wine or vinegar and drunk. The leaves boyled in wine and drunk is good to ſtay the bleeding of the Hemorrhoidal veins, the ſpitting of blood, and womens Courſes that flow too much, and helpeth the Jaundiſe, the Collick, and the bitings of the Spider <hi>Plalangium,</hi> the Viper, and all other venemous Serpents, except the Aſpe. The bark is as effectual or rather more to all the purpoſes aforeſaid. It is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported that the Egyptians uſe the wood hereof to cure the French diſeaſe with as good ſucceſſe as others doe with <hi>Lignum vitae,</hi> and give it alwayes to ſuch as have the Lepry, ſcab, puſhes, ulcers or the like, and helpeth the Dropſie ariſing from the hardneſſe and ſtopping of the Spleene, as alſo melancholly and the black Jaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe that ariſeth thereof. Cups or Cans made thereof, and drunk in, is good for Splenitick perſons.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The manner of Adminiſtring it.</head>
                  <p>It is uſed chiefly in Decoctions and diet drinks.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>It is good for the hardneſſe of the Spleene, if the root or leaves, or young branches be boyled in Wine or Vinegar and applied. The barke and leaves boyled in Wine, and the mouth and teeth often waſhed therewith, helpeth the tooth-ache, being dropped into the ears eaſeth the pain thereof, and is good for the redneſſe and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering of the eyes. The ſaid Decoction with ſome Hony put thereto is good to ſtay gangreens, and fretting ulcers; the ſaid decoction is alſo
<pb facs="tcp:118548:30"/>
good to waſh thoſe that are ſubject to lice and nits. The aſhes of the wood are uſed for all the aforeſaid effects, and beſides doth quicly help the bliſters raiſed by burnings or ſcaldings by fire or water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch things as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The extract. Salt.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 49. Of <hi>Tanſie.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine <hi>Tanacetum,</hi> becauſe the yellow Flowers ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered in due time, do not dye or wither ſpeedily; in Engliſh, Tanſie. It is hot and dry in the ſecond or third Degree.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The Decoction of Garden. or common Tanſie, or the juice drunke in Wine is a ſingular remedy for all the griefs of the Vrine to provoke it being ſtopped, to help thoſe that have the ſtrangury, and have weak reins and kidneyes, and that cannot make their water but by drops. It expelleth wind, in the ſtomach or bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, procureth womens Courſes, and expelleth windineſſe in the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. It is much uſed in Lent and in the beginning of the Spring (while the herb is young and tender) to make Tanſies, and are very profitable for thoſe ſtomacks that are troubled with bad humours cleaving thereunto, both to help to digeſt them, and by clearing the ſtomach of them, to carry them away downward. The ſeed is given to children to kill worms; and the juice given in drink is as effectual for the ſame. The root preſerved in Sugar, is a remedy for them that have the cold Gout, if they take thereof faſting for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain dayes together.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The manner of Adminiſtering it.</head>
                  <p>It is given in Decoction, or in juice.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>Being boyled in Oyle, it is very profitably applied to comfort the Sinewes that are ſhrunk by cramps, or are in pain through cold.
<pb facs="tcp:118548:30"/>
If it be bruiſed and ſmelled unto often, as alſo applied to the lower parts of the belly, it is found to be profitable for ſuch women as are given to miſcarry in child-bearing, to cauſe them to go out their full time without danger or loſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The hurtfull qualitie.</head>
                  <p>It is hurtful to young perſons and chollerick bodies.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch things as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled water.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 50. Of <hi>Thyme.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine, <hi>Thymus</hi> and <hi>Thymum;</hi> in Engliſh, Thyme. It is hot and dry in the third Degree.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Duration.</head>
                  <p>It will keep good a year.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>Thyme doth help ſomewhat to purge flegm, if it be taken with Hony, Salt, and Vinegar. The Decoction thereof is good for thoſe that are troubled with ſhortneſſe of breath, killeth worms in the belly, procureth the monethly courſes of women, expelleth the after Birth or Secundine after it hath holpen the delivery of the child and cauſeth tough flegme to be eaſily brought away, being taken with Honey in an Electuary, and helpeth alſo thoſe that are dull ſighted. It is of good uſe in meats and broths, to warm and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort the ſtomach, and to help to break wind as well for the ſick as the ſound. It is very profitable in the Collick, and Iliack and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phritick paſſions, and moſt excellent againſt Melancholly, and ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings of the Matrix, and diſſolveth clotted or congealed blood in the body, <hi>Aetius</hi> ſaith, that foure drams of dried Thyme in powder being given (in Oxymel faſting) to them that have the Gout, it helpeth them, for it purgeth Choller and other ſharp hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and that if one dram thereof be given faſting with meade,
<pb facs="tcp:118548:31"/>
it diſſolveth the hard ſwellings of the belly. It is profitable for thoſe that have ſwellings in their ſides, and pains in their loynes and hips: it is likewiſe given faſting to thoſe that have great pains in their eyes and are blear-eyed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The manner of Adminiſtering it.</head>
                  <p>It is chiefly given in Powder, or in Decoction.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The Decoction thereof diſſolveth tumours or ſwellings when they are freſh, being bathed therewith. The juice thereof being anointed or bathed on the place with ſome Vinegar, taketh away looſe or hanging warts. It helpeth thoſe that have the <hi>Sciatica</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied with wine and meale, and helpeth the ſwollen cods being laid thereto. It is uſed in bathes to expel wind and to eaſe the joynt-gout.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Doſe.</head>
                  <p>It is given in powder from a dram to two or three drams.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch Medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled water. Spirit. Chymical Oyle. Syrupe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 51. Of <hi>Vex vain.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine, <hi>Verbena,</hi> and <hi>Verbenaca;</hi> in Engliſh. Vex vain, and Pigeons graſſe, becauſe Pigeons delight to be amongſt it. It is hot and dry, bitter and binding, cleanſing and healing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>It is an opener of obſtructions, helpeth the yellow Jaundiſe, the Dropſy and the Gout, as alſo the defect of the Reins and Lungs, and generally all inward pains and torments of the body, the leaves being boyled and drunk. The ſame is held to be good againſt the biting of Serpents and venemous beaſts, and the Plague or Peſtilence, againſt both Tertian and Quartane Agues, killeth and expelleth Wormes, and cauſeth a good colour in the face and body, ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb facs="tcp:118548:31"/>
as well as correcteth the diſeaſes of the Liver and ſpleen, is very effectual in all diſeaſes of the ſtomach and lungs, as Coughs, ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Breath, and wheeſing, and expelleth the ſtone in the Reins. It healeth all inward wounds, ſtayeth bleedings and flues of the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. It is very profitable in cold diſeaſes of the head and eyes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraineth luſt, nd doth facilitate or haſten the birth in hand labours of women. The diſtilled Water is uſeful for the aforeſaid diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The manner of Adminiſtring it.</head>
                  <p>It is chiefly uſed in Decoction.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>It healeth all wounds, and ſtayeth bleedings, and uſed with ſome honey, healeth all old Vlcers and Fiſtulaes in the legs or other parts of the body, and alſo Vlcers of the mouth; or uſed with Hogs greaſe, it helpeth the ſwellings and paines of the ſecret parts of Man or Woman, as alſo the Piles or Hemorrhoids. Applied with ſome Oyle of Roſes and Vinegar unto the forehead and Temples, it helpeth to eaſe the old pains of the head, and is good for thoſe that are fallen into a Frenſy. The leaves bruiſed or the juice of them mixed with ſome Vinegar, doth cleanſe the skin, and taketh away all Morphew, Freckles, puſtulaes, or the like inflammations and deformities of the skin in any part of the body. The leaves bruiſed with Oyle of Roſes and Vinegar, or the Decoction of it made in Oyle of Roſes keepeth the haires from falling, being bathed or anointed therewith. The Decoction of the leaves and roots help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the tooth-ache. The leaves bruiſed and boyled in Hogs greaſe, helpeth the Quinſie, ſwelling of the throat and the Gout being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied warm. The diſtilled water of the herb when it is in his full ſtrength, dropped into the eyes, cleanſeth them from films, clouds or miſt that darkens the ſight, and comforteth the Optick nerves, and it good alſo to heal old ſores or green wounds.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch Medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled water, Oyntment.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:118548:32"/>
               <head>CHAP. 53. Of <hi>Violets.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine, <hi>Viola,</hi> and <hi>Viola martia;</hi> in Engliſh Violet. The garden and field Violets are cold and moiſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Duration.</head>
                  <p>It will keep good a yeare.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>Violets are uſed to cool any heat or diſtemperature of the body, inflammations in the eyes, in the mother, or in the Fundament when they are fallen down and are full of pain, Impoſtumes alſo and hot ſwellings, to drink the Decoction of the leaves or flowers made with wine or water: it likewiſe eaſeth pains in the head cauſed through want of reſt. A dram of the dried leaves of the flowers of Violets doth purge the body of Chollerick humours, and aſſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the heat, being taken in a draught of wine, or other drink, The powder of the purple leaves of the flowers onely pickt and dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and drunk in powder with water, is ſaid to help the Quinſie, and the Falling-ſickneſſe in children, eſpecially in the beginning of the diſeaſe. The ſeed being taken reſiſteth the force of the Scorpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The herb or flowers while they are freſh, or the flowers when they are dry are effectual in the Pleuriſie and all other diſeaſes of the Lungs, to lenifie the ſharpneſſe of hot Rheumes, and the hoarſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the throat, the heat alſo of the Urine, and the ſharpneſſe thereof, and all pains of the back or reins or bladder. It is good alſo for the Liver and the Jaundiſe, and in all hot Agues, helping to cool the heat, and quench thirſt: but the Syrupe of Violets is of moſt uſe and of better effect being taken in ſome convenient liquor, and if a little of the juice or Syrupe of Lemons be put to it, or a few drops of the oyle of Vitriol, it is made thereby the more power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to cool the heat and to quench the thirſt, and beſides the effect, giveth to the drink a Claretwine colour, and a fine tart relliſh plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to the taſt. Violets taken or made up with Honey doth more cleanſe then coole, and with Sugar contrariwiſe. The dried flowers of Violets are accounted among the Cordial flowers, and
<pb facs="tcp:118548:32"/>
are uſed in Cordials, drinks, Powders and other medicines, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally where cooling Cordials, as Roſes and Sanders are uſed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The manner of Administring it.</head>
                  <p>It is uſed in Decoction, Syrupe, Powder, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>Being outwardly applied, they mitigate all kind of hot inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations in the eyes, in the mother, or in the Fundament when they are fallen down and full of pain, Impoſtumes alſo and hot ſwellings mixed with Oyle of Roſes and applied, it eaſeth pains in the head, which are cauſed through want of ſleep, or in any other place ariſing of heat. The green leaves are alwayes uſed with other herbs to make Poultiſſes for inflammations or ſwellings, and to eaſe pains whereſoever ariſing of heat, and for the Piles alſo being fried with yolks of Egs and applied thereto. The oyle of Violets is good for the foreſaid purpoſes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch Medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled Water. Syrupe both ſimple and compound. Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lep of Violets. Trochiſces, Conſerve, Tincture, Vinegar of Violets. Extract. Oyle.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 53. Of <hi>Water Creſſes.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine <hi>Nasturtium aquaticum;</hi> in Engliſh Water Creſſes. They are hot and drie in the ſecond Degree.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>Water Creſſes are good againſt the Scurvie, and to cleanſe the blood and humours, and for all the other uſes whereunto Brooklime is before ſaid to be available, as to break the ſtone, provoke urine and Womens Courſes, and is very uſeful in the Green ſickneſſe. It is very uſual in the Spring to make Pottage thereof, which is very wholſome, and cleanſeth the blood, and groſſe humours. It is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable in ſtoppings of the Liver and Spleene, and in the Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118548:33"/>
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The Decoction thereof is ſaid to be good to waſh foul and filthy ulcers, thereby to cleanſe them, and make them the fitter to heale. The leaves or the juice is good to be applied to the face or other parts troubled with freckles, pimples, ſpots or the like at night, and taken away, or waſhed away in the morning. The juice mixed with Vinegar, and the fore part of the head bathed therewith, is very good for thoſe that are dull and drowſie, or have the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thargy.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch Medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled water. The Spirit.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 54. Of <hi>Wood Sage.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine <hi>Salvia agrestis;</hi> in Engliſh, Wood Sage, Wilde Sage, and Garlick Sage. It is hot and dry in the ſecond Degree.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Duration.</head>
                  <p>It will keep good a year.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>The Decoction thereof is good to be given to thoſe whoſe urine is ſtayed, for it provoketh it and Womens Courſes alſo. It is thought to be good againſt the French poxe, becauſe the Decoction thereof drunk doth provoke ſweat, digeſteth humours, and diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth ſwellings and nodes in the fleſh. The Decoction of the hearb rather green then day made with wine, and taken is accounted a ſafe and ſure remedy for thoſe who by fals, bruiſes or beatings doubt ſome vein to be inwardly broken, to diſperſe and avoid the congealed blood, and to cloſe up the Vein, and is alſo good for ſuch as are inwardly burſten; the ſame alſo is good for the Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118548:33"/>
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>Being bruiſed and applied in manner of a Poultis it helpeth burſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. The juice of the herb, or the powder thereof dried is good for moiſt ulcers and ſores in the legs or other parts to dry them, and thereby to cauſe them to heal the more ſpeedily: It is no leſſe effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual alſo in green wounds, to be uſed upon any occaſion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch Medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled water.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 55. Of <hi>Wood Sorell.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Names and Temperament.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Latine, <hi>Lujula</hi> and <hi>Alleluja,</hi> becauſe about that time it is in flower; <hi>Alleluja</hi> was wont to be ſung in the Churches in Engliſh, Wood Sorrell, Wood Sower, Stubwort, and Sorrell Dubois. It is cold and dry in the ſecond Degree.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Duration.</head>
                  <p>It will keep long dry, but we may find it almoſt all the year.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The inward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>It is more effectual then other Sorels are, eſpecially in hindering the putrifaction of blood and ulcers in the mouth and body, and in cooling heats, and inflammations, to quench thirſt, to ſtrengthen a weak ſtomach, to procure an appetite, to ſtay vomiting, and moſt excellent in any contagious ſickneſſe or peſtilential Feaver. The Syrupe made of the juice is effectual in all the cauſes aforeſaid, and ſo is the diſtilled water alſo.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118548:34"/>
                  <head>The manner of Adminiſtring it.</head>
                  <p>It is given in Decoction, or in juice:</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>Spunges or Linnen clothes wet in the juice, and applied to any hot tumors and inflammations doth exceedingly cool and heal them; the ſame juice taken into the mouth and there gargled for ſome time, and after ſpit forth and freſh taken, will wonderfully help a ſtinking foule Canker or Vlcer therein, and helpeth well alſo to ſtay any hot defluxions or Catarrhes upon the throat and lungs: It is alſo ſingular good in wounds, punctures, thruſts, and ſtabs into the body to ſtay bleeding, and to cleanſe and heale the wounds ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſuch Medicines as are made thereof.</head>
                  <p>The diſtilled Water; Conſerve, Syrupe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:118548:34"/>
            <head>The Alphebetical Table of ſuch diſeaſes as are mentioned in this <hi>Second Part.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>A</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>ABortion, <hi>See Miſcarrying</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Aches <hi>cold, Chap.</hi> 27</item>
                     <item>Afterbirth, <hi>chap.</hi> 2. 9. 16. 17. 30. 32. 38. 40. 50</item>
                     <item>Agues, <hi>to cure, chap.</hi> 17. 21. 43, 44. 45. 47</item>
                     <item>Agues <hi>of long continuance, chap.</hi> 7</item>
                     <item>Ague <hi>tertian, chap.</hi> 22. 28, 44. 51</item>
                     <item>Ague <hi>quartane, chap.</hi> 22. 26. 44. 51</item>
                     <item>Agues <hi>hot; chap.</hi> 11. 20. 34. 52</item>
                     <item>Almonds <hi>ſwollen, chap.</hi> 15</item>
                     <item>Appetite <hi>to provoke, chap.</hi> 2. 10. 28. 35. 39. 45. 55</item>
                     <item>Apoplexie, <hi>chap.</hi> 13. 24</item>
                     <item>Apoſtumes, <hi>chap.</hi> 1, 21. 22. 28. 41. 45. 52</item>
                     <item>Apoſtume <hi>hot, chap.</hi> 31</item>
                     <item>Arthritical <hi>pains, chap.</hi> 13</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>B</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>BAck pained, <hi>chapter,</hi> 13. 31 52</item>
                     <item>Back <hi>weak chap.</hi> 9</item>
                     <item>Barrenneſſe, <hi>chap.</hi> 9. 27</item>
                     <item>Beard, <hi>ſcurvineſſe thereof, chap.</hi> 23</item>
                     <item>Belly <hi>pained, chap.</hi> 7. 8.</item>
                     <item>Bees <hi>ſtinging, chap.</hi> 20. 39</item>
                     <item>Bile <hi>or</hi> Botch, <hi>chap.</hi> 45</item>
                     <item>Belly <hi>to looſe, chap.</hi> 35</item>
                     <item>Belly <hi>pained, chapter</hi> 14. 26 28</item>
                     <item>Birth <hi>to bring away, chap.</hi> 2. 4. 17. 30. 38. 50. 51</item>
                     <item>Blackneſſe <hi>and ſpots;</hi> ſee <hi>Spots and Bruiſes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Bladder to cleanſe, <hi>chap.</hi> 17</item>
                     <item>Bladder <hi>pained, chapter</hi> 13. 16. 52.</item>
                     <item>Bleeding <hi>inward, chap.</hi> 18. 26. 37. 51. 55</item>
                     <item>Blood <hi>ſpitting, chap.</hi> 19. 33. 35, 36, 37, 48</item>
                     <item>Blood <hi>piſſing, chap.</hi> 43</item>
                     <item>Blood <hi>vomiting, chap.</hi> 1. 35.</item>
                     <item>Blood <hi>congealed, chap.</hi> 3. 5. 8. 15. 31. 50. 54</item>
                     <item>Blood <hi>to cleanſe, chap.</hi> 4. 23. 42. 44. 45. 53</item>
                     <item>Blood <hi>to increaſe, chap.</hi> 12</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:118548:35"/>Blood <hi>hot, Chap.</hi> 20. 22. 45. 47</item>
                     <item>Bones <hi>broken, chap.</hi> 5</item>
                     <item>Bones <hi>broken to draw out. chap.</hi> 10. 41</item>
                     <item>Botches, <hi>chap.</hi> 23. 45</item>
                     <item>Bots <hi>in horſes, chap.</hi> 38</item>
                     <item>Bowels <hi>pained, chap.</hi> 37</item>
                     <item>Brain <hi>cold, chap.</hi> 3</item>
                     <item>Breaſts <hi>of Women pained, chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> 47</item>
                     <item>Breaſts <hi>ſore, chap.</hi> 35</item>
                     <item>Breaſts <hi>ſwollen, chap.</hi> 30</item>
                     <item>Breaſts <hi>cancerous, chap.</hi> 7</item>
                     <item>Breath <hi>ſhort, chap.</hi> 11. 14. 16. 17. 21. 23. 27. 31. 36. 38. 41. 50. 51</item>
                     <item>Breath <hi>ſtinking, chap.</hi> 44</item>
                     <item>Bruiſes <hi>and fals, chapter,</hi> 3. 5. 6. 7. 8. 15. 18. 21. 27. 29. 30. 31. 54</item>
                     <item>Burning <hi>and ſcalding, chap.</hi> 1. 13. 20. 23. 28. 31. 48</item>
                     <item>Burſtings, <hi>ſee Ruptures.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>C</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>CAncers <hi>chapter,</hi> 20. 26. 44. 55</item>
                     <item>Cancer <hi>fistulous, chap.</hi> 22</item>
                     <item>Cankers <hi>in the mouth, chap.</hi> 26. 55</item>
                     <item>Cancers <hi>fretting, chap.</hi> 38</item>
                     <item>Carbuncles <hi>chap.</hi> 23. 38. 41</item>
                     <item>Catarrhe, <hi>ſee Rheume.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Child <hi>dead to bring away, chap.</hi> 4. 17. 32. 40.</item>
                     <item>Choller <hi>to purge, chapter,</hi> 17. 47. 50. 52</item>
                     <item>Choller <hi>to repreſſe, chapter.</hi> 46</item>
                     <item>Chollericke <hi>ſtomackes. chapter,</hi> 46</item>
                     <item>Cod <hi>ſwollen, chap.</hi> 14. 15</item>
                     <item>Collick, <hi>chap.</hi> 3. 6. 8. 12. 13. 29. 40. 48. 50</item>
                     <item>Conſumption, <hi>chap.</hi> 26. 34</item>
                     <item>Contagious <hi>diſeaſes, chap.</hi> 55</item>
                     <item>Contuſion, <hi>ſee Bruiſes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Convulſions <hi>and Cramps, chap.</hi> 13. 27. 32</item>
                     <item>Corns, <hi>chap.</hi> 20. 23</item>
                     <item>Cough, <hi>chap.</hi> 11. 14. 16 17. 21. 23. 26. 27, 28, 30. 31, 34. 41. 51.</item>
                     <item>Courſes <hi>to provoke, chapter,</hi> 2. 4. 8. 9. 15. 17. 21. 23. 27. 28. 30. 31. 32. 38. 39. 40: 44 48. 50. 53. 54.</item>
                     <item>Courſes <hi>to ſtay, chap.</hi> 1. 7. 14. 18. 20. 22. 26. 33. 34. 35. 37. 43. 45</item>
                     <item>Cramp, <hi>ſee Convulſion.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Crude <hi>and raw humours to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel chap.</hi> 3</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>D</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>Dandraffe, <hi>chapter.</hi> 41</item>
                     <item>Deafneſſe, <hi>chap.</hi> 39. 45</item>
                     <item>Digeſtion <hi>to help, chapter.</hi> 6. 12</item>
                     <item>Diſlocations, <hi>chapter</hi> 23</item>
                     <item>Dog <hi>mad, biting thereof, chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> 28</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:118548:35"/>Dropſie. <hi>chap.</hi> 4. 7. 14. 17. 21. 23. 26. 30. 32. 47. 48. 51: 53</item>
                     <item>Dyſentery <hi>flux. chap.</hi> 37</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>E</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>Eares <hi>pained. chap.</hi> 28. 30. 31. 48</item>
                     <item>Eares <hi>inflamed. chap.</hi> 21</item>
                     <item>Eares <hi>running. Chap.</hi> 22</item>
                     <item>Eares, <hi>noiſe therein, chap.</hi> 21 31. 39</item>
                     <item>Eruptions <hi>of the skin, chap.</hi> 20. 31</item>
                     <item>Eryſipelas; See <hi>wildfire.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Eyes <hi>red. chap.</hi> 1. 22. 24. 30. 41. 47. 48. 52</item>
                     <item>Eyes <hi>blood ſhotten. chap.</hi> 14</item>
                     <item>Eyes <hi>watery, chap.</hi> 1</item>
                     <item>Eyes <hi>to cleanſe. chap.</hi> 51</item>
                     <item>Eyes, <hi>ſpots therein. chap.</hi> 7. 9: 41. 51</item>
                     <item>Eyes <hi>ſwollen. chap.</hi> 30</item>
                     <item>Eyes <hi>pained. chap.</hi> 50</item>
                     <item>Eyes <hi>blear. chap.</hi> 50</item>
                     <item>Eyes <hi>films therein, chap.</hi> 7</item>
                     <item>Eyes <hi>black and blew. chapter.</hi> 32</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>F</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>FAce <hi>pale. chap.</hi> 21. 42. 51</item>
                     <item>Face. <hi>ſpots thereof. chapter</hi> 3. 38. 41</item>
                     <item>Face <hi>to make faire. chap.</hi> 23. 32</item>
                     <item>Falling <hi>ſickneſſe. chapter</hi> 15. 16. 21. 30. 32. 34. 52</item>
                     <item>Falls. See <hi>Bruiſes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Feaver <hi>burning. chap.</hi> 1. 10. 25. 45</item>
                     <item>Feaver <hi>peſtilential. chap.</hi> 10. 45. 47. 55</item>
                     <item>Feaver <hi>hecticke. chap.</hi> 25</item>
                     <item>Felon. <hi>chap.</hi> 23. 41</item>
                     <item>Fiſtulaes, <hi>chap.</hi> 5. 3</item>
                     <item>Fiſtula <hi>of the Leg. chapter</hi> 51</item>
                     <item>Fleas <hi>to kill. chap.</hi> 39</item>
                     <item>Flegme <hi>to purge. chap.</hi> 17. 51</item>
                     <item>Flegme <hi>tough. chap.</hi> 21. 28. 39. 44. 50</item>
                     <item>Flux <hi>of the belly. chap.</hi> 3. 19. 20. 22. 34. 35. 45. 51</item>
                     <item>Flux <hi>bloody. chap.</hi> 22. 26. 33. 35. 37. 43. 45</item>
                     <item>Fluxes <hi>in women. Chapter</hi> 18.</item>
                     <item>Freckles <hi>chap.</hi> 15. 17. 31. 38 41. 53</item>
                     <item>Frenſie. <hi>chap.</hi> 20. 34. 51</item>
                     <item>French <hi>Pox: chapter</hi> 15. 41. 48. 54</item>
                     <item>Fundament <hi>inflamed. chapter</hi> 52</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>G</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>Gall <hi>ſtopt. chap.</hi> 7. 47</item>
                     <item>Galling <hi>of the skin. chap.</hi> 45</item>
                     <item>Gangreen. <hi>chap.</hi> 5. 48</item>
                     <item>Gonorrhaea; See <hi>running of the Reins.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:118548:36"/>Gout, <hi>chapter.</hi> 13. 24. 28. 32. 50. 51</item>
                     <item>Gout <hi>cold, chap.</hi> 49. 51</item>
                     <item>Gravel, <hi>chap.</hi> 16: 18. 31. 45</item>
                     <item>Green <hi>ſickneſſe, chap.</hi> 47. 53</item>
                     <item>Gripings <hi>of the belly, chap.</hi> 31</item>
                     <item>Groſſe <hi>humours to purge, chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> 21</item>
                     <item>Gums <hi>bleeding, chap.</hi> 19</item>
                     <item>Gums <hi>ſore, chap.</hi> 5</item>
                     <item>Gums <hi>to ſtrengthen, chap.</hi> 32</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>H</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>HAir <hi>falling, chapter</hi> 23. 28. 31. 35. 51</item>
                     <item>Head-ache, <hi>chap.</hi> 10. 11. 14</item>
                     <item>Head-ache <hi>of cold, chap.</hi> 17. 27. 51</item>
                     <item>Head-ache <hi>of heat, chapter</hi> 20 52</item>
                     <item>Head-ache <hi>in Children, chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 47</item>
                     <item>Head <hi>itching, chap.</hi> 21</item>
                     <item>Head <hi>ſcabbed, chap.</hi> 27</item>
                     <item>Head <hi>to purge, chap.</hi> 28</item>
                     <item>Head <hi>cold, chap.</hi> 6. 51</item>
                     <item>Heart <hi>to comfort, chap.</hi> 3. 10. 17. 19, 24. 45. 47</item>
                     <item>Heat <hi>to aſſwage, chap.</hi> 52. 55</item>
                     <item>Hemorrhoides <hi>to help, chap.</hi> 7. 11. 51. 52</item>
                     <item>Hemorrhoides <hi>to provoke, chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 28</item>
                     <item>Hemorrhoides <hi>bleeding, chapter.</hi> 33. 48</item>
                     <item>Hemorrhoides <hi>painful, chapter</hi> 27</item>
                     <item>Hicket, <hi>Chap.</hi> 19. 35</item>
                     <item>Hips <hi>pained, chap.</hi> 50</item>
                     <item>Hip <hi>gout; ſee Sciatica.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Hoarſneſſe, <hi>chap.</hi> 16. 34. 35. 52</item>
                     <item>Hot <hi>eruptions, chap.</hi> 20. 22</item>
                     <item>Humours <hi>to digeſt, chap.</hi> 54</item>
                     <item>Hyſterical <hi>fits; ſee Mother fits.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>I</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>JAundiſe, <hi>chap.</hi> 5. 7. 16. 21. 25. 26. 30. 32. 43. 44. 45. 47. 48. 51. 52</item>
                     <item>Jaundiſe <hi>black, chap.</hi> 48</item>
                     <item>Iliacke <hi>paſsion, chap.</hi> 50</item>
                     <item>Impoſtume; <hi>ſee Apoſtume:</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Inflammations, <hi>chap.</hi> 1. 9. 11. 20. 22. 25. 34. 45. 46. 47. 51. 52. 55</item>
                     <item>Inward <hi>parts hurt, chap.</hi> 13</item>
                     <item>Joynt-gout, <hi>chap.</hi> 50</item>
                     <item>Joynt-cold. <hi>chap.</hi> 32</item>
                     <item>Itch, <hi>chap.</hi> 7. 32. 41. 45</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>K</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>KErnels, <hi>to diſſolve, chap.</hi> 7. 45</item>
                     <item>Kibes, <hi>chapter</hi> 28</item>
                     <item>Kidneyes <hi>ulcerated, chap.</hi> 37</item>
                     <item>Kings-Evil, <hi>chap.</hi> 7. 38. 45</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>L</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>LEg <hi>ſore, chapter.</hi> 7</item>
                     <item>Leg <hi>ſwollen, chap.</hi> 4</item>
                     <item>Legs <hi>fiſtula thereof, chap.</hi> 51</item>
                     <item>Leproſie, <hi>chap.</hi> 32. 48</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:118548:36"/>Lethargy <hi>chap.</hi> 28. 39. 53</item>
                     <item>Lice <hi>to kil. chap.</hi> 21. 48</item>
                     <item>Limbs <hi>weary. chap.</hi> 32</item>
                     <item>Litharge <hi>taken. chap.</hi> 30</item>
                     <item>Liver <hi>ſtopt. chap.</hi> 2. 3. 5. 7. 19. 30. 31. 42. 44. 47. 53.</item>
                     <item>Liver <hi>hot. chap.</hi> 19. 25. 47.</item>
                     <item>Liver <hi>to ſtrengthen, chap.</hi> 51</item>
                     <item>Liver <hi>oppreſt. chap.</hi> 35</item>
                     <item>Liver-grown. <hi>chap.</hi> 5. 32</item>
                     <item>Loathing <hi>of meat. chapter.</hi> 39</item>
                     <item>Loynes <hi>pained. chap.</hi> 50</item>
                     <item>Lungs <hi>ſtopt. chapter</hi> 32. 41. 52</item>
                     <item>Lungs <hi>inflamed, chapter</hi> 46. 52</item>
                     <item>Lungs <hi>ulcerated. chapter</hi> 36 37</item>
                     <item>Lungs, <hi>Conſumption thereof. chap.</hi> 34</item>
                     <item>Luſt <hi>to provoke. chap.</hi> 8</item>
                     <item>Luſt <hi>to abate. chap.</hi> 51</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>M</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>MAtrix <hi>pained. chap.</hi> 33</item>
                     <item>Matrix <hi>ſtopt. chap.</hi> 50</item>
                     <item>Matrix <hi>hard. Chap.</hi> 23</item>
                     <item>Melancholly. <hi>chapter</hi> 17. 50</item>
                     <item>Milk <hi>curled. chap.</hi> 30</item>
                     <item>Miſcarrying. <hi>chap.</hi> 49</item>
                     <item>Morphew. <hi>chap.</hi> 7. 15. 31. 41. 51</item>
                     <item>Mother <hi>fits, chapter</hi> 17. 27. 39.</item>
                     <item>Mother <hi>pained, chap.</hi> 7. 15 27, 31. 33</item>
                     <item>Mother <hi>inflamed. chapter</hi> 17 52</item>
                     <item>Mother <hi>hard. chapter,</hi> 17. 23. 32</item>
                     <item>Mother <hi>windineſſe thereof, chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 49</item>
                     <item>Mother, <hi>cold diſeaſes thereof. chap.</hi> 6. 27</item>
                     <item>Mouth <hi>ſore. chap.</hi> 5. 31. 42. 44. 45. 55</item>
                     <item>Mouth <hi>bleeding. chap.</hi> 22. 37</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>N</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>NEeſing <hi>to provoke, Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 9</item>
                     <item>Nephritick <hi>paſsion, chap.</hi> 50</item>
                     <item>Nits <hi>to kill, chap.</hi> 48</item>
                     <item>Nodes <hi>in the fleſh, chap.</hi> 54</item>
                     <item>Noſe <hi>bleeding, chap.</hi> 14. 18. 20. 22. 26. 33. 43</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>O</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>OPium <hi>too much taken. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> 17</item>
                     <item>Optick <hi>nerves to ſtrengthen. chap.</hi> 51</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>P</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>PAllat <hi>of the mouth fallen. Chapter</hi> 19</item>
                     <item>Palſie, <hi>ch.</hi> 13. 24</item>
                     <item>Peſtilential <hi>botch. ch.</hi> 23</item>
                     <item>Peſtilence. <hi>chapter</hi> 7. 15. 23. 28. 41. 51</item>
                     <item>Peſtilential <hi>Feaver, See Feaver.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:118548:37"/>Piles; See <hi>Hemorrhoides.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Pip <hi>in Poultrie. chap.</hi> 38</item>
                     <item>Pimples. <hi>chap.</hi> 15. 41. 53</item>
                     <item>Plague. <hi>chap.</hi> 3. 7. 15. 41 51</item>
                     <item>Plague-ſore. <hi>chap.</hi> 28. 35. 38. 41. 45</item>
                     <item>Pleurifie. <hi>chap.</hi> 8. 34. 41. 52</item>
                     <item>Poyſon. <hi>chap.</hi> 3. 15. 35</item>
                     <item>Punctures, <hi>or thruſts. chap.</hi> 55</item>
                     <item>Puſtules. <hi>chap.</hi> 47. 48. 51</item>
                     <item>Putrefaction <hi>to hinder. Chapter</hi> 55</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Q</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>QVartane <hi>Ague;</hi> See <hi>Ague.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Quinſie. <hi>Chap.</hi> 21. 51. 52</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>R</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>REines <hi>to ſtrengthen. chap.</hi> 9. 49</item>
                     <item>Reins <hi>pained. chap.</hi> 16. 52</item>
                     <item>Reines <hi>hot. chap.</hi> 47</item>
                     <item>Reins <hi>to cleanſe. chap.</hi> 17. 31. 50</item>
                     <item>Reines <hi>running thereof. chap.</hi> 22. 25. 37</item>
                     <item>Rheumes. <hi>chap.</hi> 11. 27</item>
                     <item>Rheume <hi>cold. chap.</hi> 9. 27</item>
                     <item>Rheume <hi>hot. chap.</hi> 20. 34. 52. 55</item>
                     <item>Ringworm; See <hi>Tetter.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Ruptures. <hi>chapter</hi> 1. 3. 5. 18. 26. 29. 37. 54</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>S</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>SAdneſſe. <hi>chap.</hi> 17</item>
                     <item>Scab. <hi>chap.</hi> 25. 31. 38. 41. 48</item>
                     <item>Scab running. <hi>chap.</hi> 41</item>
                     <item>Scalds; See <hi>Burnings.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Sciatica. <hi>chap.</hi> 39. 50</item>
                     <item>Scurfe. <hi>chap.</hi> 15. 41</item>
                     <item>Scurvie. <hi>chapter</hi> 4. 42. 53</item>
                     <item>Scorpion <hi>ſtinging thereof. chap.</hi> 45. 52</item>
                     <item>Secundine; See <hi>After-birth.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Secret <hi>parts ſwollen. Chapter</hi> 51</item>
                     <item>Serpents <hi>biting thereof. chap.</hi> 2. 12. 13. 19. 21. 23. 51</item>
                     <item>Sharp <hi>humours to purge. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 50</item>
                     <item>Shingles. <hi>chap.</hi> 20</item>
                     <item>Side <hi>pained. chap.</hi> 8. 14</item>
                     <item>Side <hi>ſwollen. chap.</hi> 50</item>
                     <item>Sight <hi>weak. chapter</hi> 6. 39 50</item>
                     <item>Sight <hi>to cleanſe. chap.</hi> 9</item>
                     <item>Sinewes <hi>te ſoften. chap.</hi> 25</item>
                     <item>Sinewes <hi>ſhrunk. chapter.</hi> 41. 49</item>
                     <item>Sinewes <hi>to ſtrengthen. chapter</hi> 35. 49</item>
                     <item>Sinewes <hi>cut. ch.</hi> 23</item>
                     <item>Sinew <hi>bruiſed. chap.</hi> 31</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:118548:37"/>Skin <hi>to cleanſe. chap.</hi> 7. 13. 31 51</item>
                     <item>Skin <hi>galling thereof. Chapter</hi> 45</item>
                     <item>Sleep <hi>to procure. chap.</hi> 8. 34. 52</item>
                     <item>Sneeſing <hi>to provoke. chap.</hi> 9</item>
                     <item>Saint <hi>Anthonies</hi> fire. See <hi>Wild fire.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Sores <hi>ald and running. chap.</hi> 5. 25. 38</item>
                     <item>Sores <hi>of the head. chap.</hi> 38</item>
                     <item>Sores <hi>ſpreading. chap.</hi> 1. 22. 25</item>
                     <item>Sores <hi>to cure. chap.</hi> 5. 7. 18. 22. 41</item>
                     <item>Speech <hi>loſt. chap.</hi> 23</item>
                     <item>Sperm <hi>to increaſe, chap.</hi> 12. 28.</item>
                     <item>Spirits <hi>faint. chap.</hi> 10. 32 35. 45</item>
                     <item>Spider <hi>againſt the venome there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. chap.</hi> 20. 44. 48</item>
                     <item>Spleen <hi>ſtopt. chap.</hi> 2. 3. 19. 21. 26. 29. 30. 31. 42. 44. 47. 53</item>
                     <item>Spleen <hi>hard. chap.</hi> 48</item>
                     <item>Spleen <hi>to ſtrengthen. chapter</hi> 51</item>
                     <item>Spots <hi>to take away. chapter</hi> 3. 6. 8. 13. 15. 17. 21. 28. 30. 31. 32. 38. 42. 53</item>
                     <item>Steel <hi>to harden. Chap.</hi> 26</item>
                     <item>Stiches <hi>in the fide. chap.</hi> 3 14. 41</item>
                     <item>Stomach <hi>to comfort. chap.</hi> 2. 6. 8. 12. 40. 50</item>
                     <item>Stomach <hi>crude or raw. chap.</hi> 2. 8. 9. 32. 40, 49</item>
                     <item>Stomach <hi>to ſtrengthen. chap.</hi> 3. 35. 55</item>
                     <item>Stomach <hi>hot, chapter,</hi> 19. 22. 46. 47</item>
                     <item>Stomach <hi>windie. chap.</hi> 17. 27 39</item>
                     <item>Stomach <hi>ſwollen. chap.</hi> 16</item>
                     <item>Stomach <hi>gnawing. chapter,</hi> 32</item>
                     <item>Stone <hi>to bring away. chap.</hi> 4. 8. 16. 17. 18. 26. 30. 31. 40. 45. 51. 53</item>
                     <item>Strangury. <hi>chap.</hi> 2. 16. 40. 49</item>
                     <item>Sun <hi>burning. chap.</hi> 7. 31</item>
                     <item>Sweat <hi>to reſtrain. Chap.</hi> 35</item>
                     <item>Sweat <hi>to provoke. chap.</hi> 54</item>
                     <item>Swellings <hi>to abate. chap.</hi> 9. 37. 47</item>
                     <item>Swellings <hi>hard to diſſolve. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 50. 54</item>
                     <item>Swellings <hi>hot. chapter</hi> 22. 46. 52</item>
                     <item>Swimming <hi>of the head. chap.</hi> 6. 14. 17. 24. 27. 38</item>
                     <item>Swoonings. <hi>chap.</hi> 32. 47</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>T</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>TEndon <hi>bruiſed. Chap.</hi> 31</item>
                     <item>Terms; See <hi>Courſes</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Tetters. <hi>chap.</hi> 7. 20. 24. 25. 41</item>
                     <item>Teeth <hi>looſe. chap.</hi> 7. 18</item>
                     <item>Teeth <hi>looſe, to make them fall out. chap.</hi> 7</item>
                     <item>Thirſt <hi>to quench. chap.</hi> 20. 45. 52. 55</item>
                     <item>Throat <hi>hoarſe, chap.</hi> 52</item>
                     <item>Throat <hi>ſore, chap.</hi> 18. 31</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:118548:38"/>Throat <hi>ſwollen, chapter</hi> 51</item>
                     <item>Throat <hi>rough, chapter</hi> 35. 46</item>
                     <item>Thorns <hi>and Splinters to draw out. ch.</hi> 9. 41.</item>
                     <item>Thruſts <hi>or ſtabs, chapter</hi> 5 55</item>
                     <item>Toothe-ache. <hi>chap.</hi> 10. 21. 31. 48. 51</item>
                     <item>Tumours <hi>hard to diſſolve. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 7. 8. 41. 50</item>
                     <item>Tumours <hi>hot. chap.</hi> 1. 55.</item>
                     <item>Tumours <hi>to help. chap.</hi> 4. 7. 9. 15. 23</item>
                     <item>Tympany. <hi>chap.</hi> 14</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>V</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>VEins broken. <hi>chapter</hi> 37. 54</item>
                     <item>Vein <hi>ſhrunk. ch.</hi> 41</item>
                     <item>Venery <hi>to provoke, ch.</hi> 9. 17 39</item>
                     <item>Venome to expel. <hi>chapter.</hi> 30. 41</item>
                     <item>Venomous <hi>Creatures ſtinging thereof. ch.</hi> 13. 15. 20. 22. 28. 32. 33. 41. 48, 51</item>
                     <item>Viper <hi>ſtinging thereof. chapter</hi> 48</item>
                     <item>Viſcous <hi>humours to digeſt. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 2</item>
                     <item>Vlcers <hi>to cure. ch.</hi> 5. 18. 23. 37. 38. 41. 48. 51. 55</item>
                     <item>Vlcers maligne. <hi>ch.</hi> 37</item>
                     <item>Vlcers moiſt, <hi>ch</hi> 54</item>
                     <item>Vlcers <hi>of the leg. chap.</hi> 51 54</item>
                     <item>Vlcers <hi>fretting<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> chap.</hi> 26. 48</item>
                     <item>Vlcers <hi>of the mouth. ch.</hi> 18. 37. 42. 44. 51. 55</item>
                     <item>Vlcers <hi>in ward. chap.</hi> 41. 45</item>
                     <item>Vlcers <hi>old. chap.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Vlcers <hi>creeping. ch.</hi> 38</item>
                     <item>Vlcers of the bowels. <hi>chapter.</hi> 45</item>
                     <item>Vlcers <hi>of the head. chapter</hi> 23. 31</item>
                     <item>Vlcers <hi>eating. chapter</hi> 7. 26</item>
                     <item>Vlcers <hi>running. chap.</hi> 31</item>
                     <item>Vlcers <hi>of the ſecret parts. ch.</hi> 5. 18. 22</item>
                     <item>Vlcers <hi>of the Lungs; ſee Lungs.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Vlcers <hi>to cleanſe. chap.</hi> 19. 32</item>
                     <item>Vlcers <hi>putrified and rotten. chap.</hi> 28. 31. 32. 37. 42. 44. 53</item>
                     <item>Vlcers <hi>fiſtulous. ch.</hi> 3</item>
                     <item>Vlcers <hi>callous, or hard, chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> 3</item>
                     <item>Vomiting <hi>to ſtay, chap.</hi> 1. 12. 35. 55</item>
                     <item>Vomit <hi>to provoke, cha.</hi> 2. 4. 6. 8. 16. 21</item>
                     <item>Vrine <hi>ſtopt. Chapter</hi> 2. 12. 18. 21. 22. 28. 30. 31. 32. 39. 44. 47. 49. 53. 54</item>
                     <item>Vrine <hi>flowing to ſtop. Chapter</hi> 24</item>
                     <item>Vrine <hi>hot and ſharp. Chapter</hi> 52</item>
                     <item>Vrine <hi>bloody. chap.</hi> 37</item>
                     <item>Vvula <hi>fallen; ſee Pallate of the mouth.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>W</label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:118548:38"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>WArts <hi>to take away. Chapter</hi> 7. 50</item>
                     <item>Waſps <hi>ſtinging thereof; Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 39</item>
                     <item>Wearineſſe <hi>of the limbs. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 32</item>
                     <item>Wens <hi>to take away. chap.</hi> 7</item>
                     <item>Wheeles <hi>and blanes. chap.</hi> 47</item>
                     <item>Wheeſing. <hi>chap.</hi> 11. 20. 30. 51</item>
                     <item>Whites <hi>in women, chap.</hi> 1. 25</item>
                     <item>Wildfire. <hi>chap.</hi> 4. 11. 20. 22. 23. 31. 34. 38. 42. 47</item>
                     <item>Wind <hi>to expel chap.</hi> 2. 6. 14. 16. 21. 30. 39. 44. 49. 50. 51</item>
                     <item>Wind <hi>in the belly. chap.</hi> 27. 39. 40. 49</item>
                     <item>Womb, <hi>cold diſeaſes thereof chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 6</item>
                     <item>Womb <hi>windie. chap.</hi> 6</item>
                     <item>Worms <hi>to kill. chap.</hi> 12. 15. 21. 22. 28. 38. 44. 45. 49. 50. 51</item>
                     <item>Wounds <hi>to cure. chap.</hi> 5. 23. 26. 29. 36: 37. 51. 55</item>
                     <item>Wounds <hi>bleeding. chap.</hi> 18: 25. 43</item>
                     <item>Wounds <hi>inflamed. chap.</hi> 1</item>
                     <item>Wounds <hi>hollow. ch.</hi> 7</item>
                     <item>Wounds <hi>green. chap.</hi> 1. 15. 18. 21. 22. 26. 31. 36. 41. 42. 54</item>
                     <item>Wounds <hi>inward. chap.</hi> 3. 5. 22. 29. 33. 41. 51. 55</item>
                     <item>Wounds <hi>of the head. chap.</hi> 11. 43</item>
                     <item>Wounds to cleanſe. <hi>chap.</hi> 19. 26</item>
                     <item>Wounds <hi>in the breaſt. chap.</hi> 1</item>
                     <item>Wounds <hi>in the bowels. chap.</hi> 1</item>
                     <item>Wounds <hi>fiſtulous. chap.</hi> 3.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Y</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>Yard <hi>bliſtered, chap.</hi> 38.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:118548:39"/>
            <head>The Books following are to be ſold by <hi>Philemon Stephens,</hi> at the guilded Lion in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard.</head>
            <p>SIx Books written by the learned Knight Sir <hi>Henry Spelman:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>De non temerandis Eccleſiis;</hi> or, of the Right and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects due unto Churches which are not to be violated.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Tythes too hot to be touched, ſhewing that Tythes are due by the Law of Nature, Scripture, and Nations; and therefore nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Jewiſh, Popiſh nor Inconvenient. Whereunto are annexed cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Treatiſes of that Argument by other Authors with a perfect Table of their Contents.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Concilia, Decreta, Leges, Conſtitutiones de Re Eccleſiarum Orbis Brittannici, ab initio Chriſtianae ibidem Religionis; cum Anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationibus non minus piis quam doctis: Opus Antiquitatis ſtudioſis apprime gratum &amp; utile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Gloſſarium eruditiſſimum: in quo priſci Ritus quamplurimi, Magistratus, Dignitates, Munera, Officia, Mores, Leges, &amp; Conſuetudines enarrantur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Pſalterium Davidis Latino-Saxonicum, à Jo. Spelmanno, Henrici F. è Patris Bibliotheca in lucem editum: ubi ad fienm uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſcujuſque Pſalmi preces optimae in animum Pſalmi reperiuntur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>De Sepultura.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Civil Magiſtrates Power in matters of Religion modeſtly debated, and impartially ſtated according to the bounds &amp; grounds of Scripture, and anſwer returned to the Objections againſt the ſame of any ſeeming weight. Written by <hi>Thomas Cobbet,</hi> Paſtor of the Church at <hi>Lyn</hi> in <hi>New-England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Gataker,</hi> B. D. his Vindication of the <hi>Annotations</hi> by him publiſhed on Jer. 10.2. Againſt the ſcurrilous Aſperſions of Mr. <hi>William Lillie,</hi> wherein the pretended grounds of Judicarie A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologie, and the Scripture proofs produced for it, are diſcuſſed and refuted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomae Gatakeri de Nomine Tetragrammato Diſſertatio; Quâ vocis</hi> Jehova, <hi>apud noſtros receptae uſus defenditur, &amp; à quorundam cavillationibus iniqis pariter atque inanibus vindicatur.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
